<chapter>
<h2>VII</h2>
<h3>THE HIGHEST IDEAL OF JNÂNA YOGA</h3>


<p>As this is the last of these classes it is better
that I give a brief <i>resumé</i> of all that I have
been trying to tell you. In the Vedas and
Upanishads we find records of some of the
very earliest religious ideas of the Hindus,
ideas that long antedated the time of Kapila,
ancient as this great sage is. He did not propound
the <i>Sânkhya</i> philosophy as a new theory
of his own. His task was to throw the light
of his genius on the vast mass of religious
theories that were existing in his time and
bring out a rational and coherent system. He
succeeded in giving India a psychology that is
accepted to the present day by all the diverse
and seemingly opposing philosophical systems
to be found among the Hindus. His masterly
analysis and his comprehensive statement of
the processes of the human mind have not yet
been surpassed by any later philosopher and
he undoubtedly laid the foundation for the
Advaita philosophy, which accepted his conclusions
as far as they went and then pushed them
a step farther, thus reaching a final unity beyond
the duality that was the last word of
the <i>Sânkhyas</i>.</p>

<p>Among the religious ideas that preceded the
time of Kapila the first groups that we see
coming up,—I mean among recognized religious
ideas, and not the very low ones, which
do not deserve the name of religion,—all
include the idea of inspiration, and revealed
book and so forth. In the earliest step, the
idea of creation is very peculiar; it is that the
whole universe is created out of zero, at the
will of God; that all this universe did not
exist, and out of nothingness all this has come.
In the next stage we find this conclusion is
questioned. The first step in Vedânta asks
this question: How can existence be produced
out of non-existence? If this universe is existent
it must have come out of something,
because it was easy for them to see that there
is nothing coming out of nothing anywhere.
All work that is going on by human hands
requires materials. Naturally, therefore, the
ancient Hindus rejected the first idea that this
world was created out of nothing, and sought
some material out of which this world was
created. The whole history of religion, in fact,
is this search for material. Out of what has
all this been produced? Apart from the question
of the efficient cause, or God, apart from
the question whether God created the universe,
the great question of all questions has been,
out of what did God create it? All the philosophies
are turning, as it were, on this
question.</p>

<p>One solution is that nature and God and
soul are eternal existences, as if three parallel
lines are running eternally, of which nature
and soul comprise what they call the dependent,
and God the independent Being. Every soul,
like every particle of matter, is perfectly dependent
on the will of God. These and many
other ideas we find already existing when the
<i>Sânkhya</i> psychology was brought forward by
Kapila. According to it, perception comes by
the transmission of the suggestion, which
causes perception first to the eyes, from the
eyes to the organs, from the organs to the
mind, the mind to the <i>buddhi</i> and from the
<i>buddhi</i> to something which is a unit, which
they call the <i>Âtman</i>. Coming to modern physiology
we know that they have found centres
for all the different sensations. First are found
the lower centres, then a higher grade of
centres, and these two will exactly correspond
with the actions of the <i>buddhi</i> and the <i>manas</i>
(mind), but not one centre has been found
which controls all the other centres, so philosophy
cannot answer what unifies all these
centres. Where and how do the centres get
unified? The centres in the brain are all different,
and there is not one centre which controls
all the others; therefore, so far as it goes,
the <i>Sânkhya</i> psychology stands unchallenged
upon this point. We must have this unification,
something upon which the sensations will
be reflected to form a complete whole. Until
there is that something I cannot have any idea
of you, or the picture, or anything else. If
we had not that unifying something we would
only see, then after a while hear, and then
feel, and while we heard a man talking we
should not see him at all, because all the centres
are different.</p>

<p>This body is made of particles which we
call matter, and it is dull and insentient. So
is what is called the fine body. The fine body,
according to the <i>Sânkhyas</i> is a little body, made
of very fine particles, so fine that no microscope
can see them. What is the use of it?
It is the receptacle of what we call mind. Just
as this gross body is the receptacle of the
grosser forces, so the fine body is the receptacle
of the finer forces, that which we call thought,
in its various modifications. First is the body,
which is gross matter, with gross force. Force
cannot exist without matter. It can only manifest
itself through matter, so the grosser forces
work through the body and those very forces
become finer; the very force which is working
in a gross form works in a fine form and becomes
thought. There is no real difference
between them, simply one is the gross and the
other the fine manifestation of the same thing.
Neither is there any difference in substance
between the fine body and the gross body. The
fine body is also material, only very fine
material.</p>

<p>Whence do all these forces come? According
to the Vedânta philosophy there are two
things in Nature, one of which they call <i>Âkâsa</i>,
which is substance, or matter, infinitely fine,
and the other they call <i>Prâna</i>. Whatever you
see, or feel, or hear, as air or earth, or anything,
is material. And everything is a form
of this <i>âkâsa</i>. It becomes finer and finer, or
grosser and grosser, and it changes under the
action of <i>Prâna</i> (universal Energy). Like
<i>âkâsa</i>, <i>prâna</i> is omnipresent, interpenetrating
everything. <i>Âkâsa</i> is like the water, and
everything else in the universe like blocks of
ice, made out of that water and floating in
it, and <i>prâna</i> is the power that changes the
<i>âkâsa</i> into all these various forms. This body
is the instrument made out of <i>âkâsa</i> for the
manifestation of <i>prâna</i> in gross forms, as muscular
motion, or walking, sitting, talking, and
so on. The fine body also is made of <i>âkâsa</i>,
a much finer form of <i>âkâsa</i>, for the manifestation
of the same <i>prâna</i> in the finer form of
thought. So, first there is this gross body,
beyond that is the fine body, and beyond that
is the <i>jiva</i> (soul), the real man. Just as these
finger nails can be pared off a hundred times
a year, and yet are still a part of our bodies,
not different, so we have not two bodies. It
is not that man has a fine and also a gross
body; it is the one body, only it remains longer
when it is a fine body, and the grosser it is the
sooner it dissolves. Just as I can cut this
nail a hundred times a year, so millions of
times I can shed this body in one æon, but the
fine body will remain. According to the dualists
this <i>jiva</i>, or the real man, is very fine,
minute.</p>

<p>So far we have seen that man is a being
who has first a gross body which dissolves
very quickly, then a fine body which remains
through æons, and lastly a <i>jiva</i>. This <i>jiva</i>,
according to the Vedânta philosophy, is eternal,
just as God is eternal, and Nature is also eternal,
but changefully eternal. The material of
Nature, the <i>prâna</i> and the <i>âkâsa</i>, are eternal,
but are changing into different forms eternally.
Matter and force are eternal, but their combinations
vary continually. The <i>jiva</i> is not
manufactured, either of <i>âkâsa</i>, or of <i>prâna</i>;
it is immaterial, and therefore will remain
for ever. It is not the result of any combination
of <i>prâna</i> and <i>âkâsa</i>, and whatever is not
the result of combination will never be destroyed,
because destruction is decomposition.
That which is not a compound cannot be
destroyed. The gross body is a compound of
<i>âkâsa</i> and <i>prâna</i> in various forms and will be
decomposed. The fine body will also be decomposed
after a long time, but the <i>jiva</i> is a
simple, and will never be destroyed. For the
same reason, we cannot say it ever was born.
Nothing simple can be born; the same argument
applies. Only that which is a compound
can be born. The whole of this nature combined
in these millions of forms is under the
will of God. God is all pervading, omniscient,
formless, everywhere, and He is directing this
nature day and night. The whole of it is
under His control. There is no independence
of any being. It cannot be. He is the
Ruler. This is the teaching of dualistic Vedânta.</p>

<p>Then the question comes, if God be the Ruler
of this universe, why did He create such a
wicked universe, why must we suffer so much?
The answer is made that it is not God’s fault.
It is our own fault that we suffer. Whatever
we sow that we reap. God does not do anything
to punish us. If a man is born poor,
or blind, or lame, he did something before he
was born in that way, something that produced
these results. The <i>jiva</i> has been existing for
all time, was never created. It has been doing
all sorts of things all the time. Whatever we
do we suffer for. If we do good we shall have
happiness, and if bad, unhappiness. This <i>jiva</i>
is by its own nature pure, but ignorance covers
its nature, says the dualist. As by evil deeds it
has covered itself with ignorance, so by good
deeds it can become conscious of its own nature
again. Just as it is eternal, so its nature is
pure. The nature of every being is pure. When
through good deeds all its sins and misdeeds
have been washed away, then the <i>jiva</i> becomes
pure again, and when he becomes pure he goes
after death by what is called <i>Devayana</i> (the
path of the gods), to heaven, or the abode of
the gods. If he has been only an ordinarily
good man he goes to what is called the “Abode
of the Fathers.”</p>

<p>When the gross body falls, the organs of
speech enter the mind. You cannot think
without words; wherever there are words there
must be thought. The mind is resolved into
the <i>prâna</i>, and the <i>prâna</i> resolves into the <i>jiva</i>.
Then the <i>jiva</i> leaves the body and goes to that
condition of reward or punishment which he
has earned by his past life. <i>Devaloka</i> is the
“place (or abode) of the gods.” The word
<i>deva</i> (god) means bright or shining one, and
corresponds to what the Christians and Mohammedans
call “angels.” According to this
teaching there are various heavenly spheres
somewhat analogous to the various heavens
described by Dante in the <i>Divine Comedy</i>.
There are the heaven of the fathers (or <i>pitris</i>),
<i>devaloka</i>, the lunar sphere, the electric sphere
and highest of all the <i>Brahmaloka</i>, the heaven
of <i>Brahma</i>. From all the lower heavens the
<i>jiva</i> returns again to human birth, but he who
attains to <i>Brahmaloka</i> lives there through all
eternity. These are the highest men who have
become perfectly unselfish, perfectly purified,
who have given up all desires, do not want to
do anything except to worship and love God.
There is a second class, who do good works,
but want some reward, want to go to heaven
in return. When they die the <i>jiva</i> goes to the
lunar sphere, where it enjoys and becomes a
<i>deva</i> (god or angel). The gods, the <i>devas</i>,
are not eternal, they have to die. In heaven
they will all die. The only deathless place is
<i>Brahmaloka</i>, where alone there is no birth and
no death. In our mythology it is said there are
also the demons, who sometimes give the gods
chase. In all mythologies you read of these
fights between the demons, or wicked angels,
and the gods and sometimes the demons conquer
the gods. In all mythologies also, you
find that the <i>devas</i> were fond of the beautiful
daughters of men. As a <i>deva</i>, the <i>jiva</i> only
reaps results of past actions, but makes no new
Karma. Only man makes Karma. Karma
means actions that will produce effects, also
those effects, or results of action. When a
man dies and becomes a <i>deva</i> he has a period
of pleasure, and during that time makes no
fresh Karma; he simply enjoys the reward of
his past good works. But when the good
Karma is worked out then the other Karma
begins to take effect.</p>

<p>In the Vedas there is no mention of hell.
But afterwards the <i>Purânas</i>, the later books in
our Scriptures, thought that no religion could
become complete without a proper attachment
of hells, and so they invented all sorts of hells,
with as many, if not more, varieties of punishment
than Dante saw in his <i>Inferno</i>, but our
books are merciful enough to say that it is
only for a period. Bad Karma is worked out
in that state and then the souls come back to
earth and get another chance. This human
form is the great chance. It is called the
<i>karmic</i> body, in which we decide our fate.
We are running in a huge circle, and this is
the point in the circle which determines the
future. So a human body is considered the
greatest body there is; man is greater than
the gods. Even they return to human birth.
So far with dualistic Vedânta.</p>

<p>Next comes a higher conception of Vedânta
philosophy, which says that these ideas are
crude. If you say there is a God who is an
infinite Being, and a soul which is also infinite,
and Nature which is also infinite, you can go
on multiplying infinites indefinitely, but that
is illogical, because each would limit the other
and there would be no real infinite. God is
both the material and the efficient cause of the
universe; He projects this universe out of
Himself. Does that mean that God has become
these walls, and this table, that God has
become the animal, the murderer and all the
evils in the world? God is pure, how can He
become all these degenerate things? He has
not. God is unchangeable, all these changes
are in Nature; just as I am a soul and have a
body, this body is not different from me in a
sense, yet I, the real “I,” in fact am not this
body. For instance, I am a child, I become a
young man, an old man, but my soul has not
changed. It remains the same soul. Similarly
the whole universe comprises all Nature, and
an infinite number of souls, or, as it were, the
infinite body of God. He is interpenetrating
the whole of it. He alone is unchangeable,
but Nature changes and soul changes. In
what way does Nature change? In its forms;
it takes fresh forms. But the soul cannot
change that way. The soul contracts and expands
in knowledge. It contracts by evil deeds;
those deeds which contract the natural knowledge
and purity of the soul are called evil
deeds. Those deeds, again, which bring out
the natural glory of the soul, are called good
deeds. All these souls were pure, but they
have become contracted by their own acts.
Still, through the mercy of God, and by doing
good deeds, they will expand and become pure
again. Every soul has the same chance, and,
in the long run, must become pure and free
itself from Nature. But this universe will not
cease, because it is infinite. This is the second
theory. The first is called dualistic Vedânta;
the second teaches that there is God, soul, and
Nature, that soul and Nature form the body of
God, and that these three form one unit. Believers
in this second theory are called qualified
non-dualists (<i>Visishtadvaitins</i>).</p>

<p>The last and highest theory is pure monism,
or as it is known in India, <i>Advaita</i>. It also
teaches that God must be both the material and
the efficient cause of this universe. As such,
God has become the whole of this universe.
This theory denies that God is the soul, and
the universe is the body, and the body is
changing. In that case what is the use of
calling God the material cause of this universe?
The material cause is the cause become
effect; the effect is nothing but the cause in
another form. Wherever you see effect, it is
the cause reproduced. If the universe is the
effect, and God the cause, this must be the
reproduction of God. If it be claimed that the
universe is the body of God and that that body
becomes contracted and fine and becomes the
cause, and out of that the universe is evolved,
then the <i>advaitist</i> says it is God Himself who
has become this universe. Now comes a very
fine question. If God has become this universe,
then everything is God. Certainly; everything
is God. My body is God, and my mind is
God, and my soul is God. Then why are there
so many <i>jivas</i>? Has God become divided into
millions and millions of <i>jivas</i>? How can that
infinite power and substance, the one Being
of the universe become divided? It is impossible
to divide infinity. How can the pure
Being become this universe? If He has become
the universe, He is changeful, and if He
is changeful, He is in Nature, and whatever
is in Nature is born and dies. If God is
changeful, He must die some day. Remember
that. Again, how much of God has become
this universe? If you say “X,” the algebraical
unknown quantity, then God is God minus “X”
now, and therefore not the same God as before
this creation, because so much of Him has
become this universe. The answer of the non-dualist
is that this universe has no real existence,
it exists in appearance only. These <i>devas</i>
and gods and angels and being born and dying,
and all this infinite number of souls coming
up and going down, all these things are mere
dreams. All is the one Infinite. The one sun
reflected on various drops of water appears to
be many, millions of globules of water reflect
so many millions of suns and in each globule
will be a perfect image of the sun, yet there
is only one sun, and so it is with all these <i>jivas</i>,
they are but reflections of the one infinite
Being. A dream cannot be without a reality,
and that reality is the one infinite Existence.
You, as body, mind, or soul, are a dream, but
what you really are is Existence-Knowledge-Bliss
Absolute. Thus says the <i>Advaitist</i>. All
these births and rebirths, this coming and going
are but parts of the dream. You are infinite.
Where can you go? The sun, moon, and the
whole universe are but a drop in your nature.
How can you be born or die? The Self was
never born, never will be born, never had father
or mother, friends or foes, for it is Existence-Knowledge-Bliss
Absolute.</p>

<p>What is the goal, according to this philosophy?
That those who receive this knowledge
are one with the universe; for them all
heavens, even <i>Brahmaloka</i>, are destroyed, the
whole dream vanishes, and they find themselves
the eternal God of the universe. They attain
their real individuality, infinitely beyond these
little selves which we now think of so much
importance. No individuality will be lost; an
infinite and eternal Individuality will be realized.
Pleasures in little things will cease. We
are finding pleasure in this little body, in this
little individuality. How much greater the
pleasure when this whole universe is in our
one body? If there be pleasure in these separate
bodies, how much more when all bodies
are one? The man who has realized this has
attained to freedom, has gone beyond the
dream and known himself in his real nature.
This is the teaching of Advaita, the non-dualistic
Vedânta.</p>

<p>These are the three steps which Vedânta
philosophy has taken, and we cannot go beyond,
because we cannot go beyond unity. When
any science reaches a unity it cannot possibly
go any farther. You cannot go beyond this
idea of the Absolute, the One Idea of the universe,
out of which everything else has evolved.
All people cannot take up this <i>Advaita</i> philosophy;
it is too hard. First of all, it is very
difficult to understand it intellectually. It
requires the sharpest of intellects, a bold understanding.
Secondly, it does not suit the vast
majority of people.</p>

<p>It is better to begin with the first of these
three steps. Then by thinking of that and
understanding it, the second one will open of
itself. Just as a race travels, so individuals
have to travel. The steps which the human
race has taken to come to the highest pinnacle
of religious thought, every individual will have
to take. Only, while the human race took
millions of years to reach from one step to
another, individuals may live the whole life
of the human race in a few years, or they may
be able to do it more quickly, perhaps in six
months. But each one of us will have to go
through these steps. Those of you who are
non-dualists can, no doubt, look back to the
period of your lives when you were strong
dualists. As soon as you think you are a body
and a mind, you will have to accept the whole
of this dream. If you have one piece you must
take the whole. The man who says, here is
this world but there is no God, is a fool, because
if there be a world there will have to be
a cause of the world, and that is what is called
God. You cannot have an effect without
knowing that there is a cause. God will only
vanish when this world vanishes. When you
have realized your one-ness with God, this
world will no longer be for you. As long as
this dream exists, however, we are bound to
see ourselves as being born and dying, but as
soon as the dream that we are bodies vanishes,
so will vanish this dream that we are being
born and dying, and so will vanish the other
dream that there is a universe. That very
thing which we now see as this universe will
appear to us as God, and that very God who
was so long external, will appear as the very
Self of our own selves. The last word of
<i>Advaita</i> is, <i>Tat tvam asi</i>,—“That thou art.”</p>

<p></p>
</chapter>
