<chapter>
<h2>I</h2>
<h3>THE SÂNKHYA COSMOLOGY</h3>

<p>Here are two words, the microcosm and
the macrocosm, the internal and the external.
We get truths from both of these by means of
experience; there is internal experience and
external experience. The truths gathered from
internal experience are psychology, metaphysics
and religion; from external experience
the physical sciences. Now a perfect truth
should be in harmony with experience in both
these worlds. The microcosm must bear testimony
to the macrocosm, and the macrocosm to
the microcosm; physical truth must have its
counterpart in the internal world, and the internal
world must have its verification in the
outside. Yet as a rule we find that many of
these truths are constantly conflicting. At one
period of the world’s history the “internals”
became supreme, and they began to fight the
“externals;” at the present time the “externals,”
the physicists, have become supreme,
and they have put down many claims of the
psychologists and metaphysicians. So far as
my little knowledge goes, I find that the really
essential parts of psychology are in perfect accordance
with the essential parts of modern
physical knowledge.</p>

<p>It is not given to every individual to be
great in every respect; it is not given to the
same race, or nation, to be equally strong in
the research of all the fields of knowledge.
The modern European nations are very strong
in their researches into external physical
knowledge, but the ancient Europeans were
weak in their researches into the internal part
of man. On the other hand, the Orientals
have not been very strong in their researches
in the external physical world, but have excelled
in their researches into the internal, and
therefore we find that some of the Oriental
theories are not in accordance with Occidental
physics, neither is Occidental psychology in
harmony with Oriental teachings on this subject.
The Oriental physicists have been criticised
by Occidental scientists. At the same
time each rests on truth, and, as we stated before,
real truth in any field of knowledge will
not contradict itself, the truths internal are in
harmony with the truths external.</p>

<p>We know the present theories of the Cosmos
according to the modern astronomers and
physicists, and at the same time we know how
wofully they hurt the old school of theologians,
and how every new scientific discovery that
is made is as a bomb thrown into their house,
and how they have attempted in every age to
put down all these researches. In the first
place, let us go over the psychological and
scientific ideas of the Orientals as to cosmology
and all that pertains to it, and you will find
how wonderfully it is in accordance with all
the latest discoveries of modern science, and
when there is anything lacking you will find
that it is on the side of modern science. We
all use the word Nature, and the old Hindu
philosophers called it by two different names,
<i>Prakriti</i>, which is almost the same as the English
word “nature,” and by the more scientific
name, <i>Avyaktam</i> (“undifferentiated”), from
which everything proceeds, out of which come
atoms and molecules, matter and force, and
mind and intellect. It is startling to find that
the philosophers and metaphysicians of India
ages ago stated that mind is but matter in a
finer form, for what are our present materialists
striving to do but to show that mind is as
much a product of nature as the body? And
so is thought; and we shall find by and by
that the intellect also comes from the same
nature which is called <i>avyaktam</i>, the undifferentiated.</p>

<p>The ancient teachers define <i>avyaktam</i> as the
“equilibrium of the three forces,” one of which
is called <i>Sattva</i>, the second <i>Rajas</i> and the third
<i>Tamas</i>. <i>Tamas</i>, the lowest force, is that of
attraction, a little higher is <i>Rajas</i>, that of repulsion,
and the highest is the control of these
two, <i>Sattva</i>, so that when the two forces, attraction
and repulsion, are held in perfect control,
or balance, by the <i>Sattva</i>, there is no
creation, no movement; but as soon as this
equilibrium is lost, the balance is disturbed and
one of these forces gets stronger than the
other. Then change and motion begin and all
this evolution goes on. This state of things
is going on cyclically, periodically; that is to
say, there is a period of disturbance of the
balance, when all these forces begin to combine
and recombine, and this universe is projected;
and there is also a period when everything
has a tendency to revert to the primal state
of equilibrium, and the time comes when a
total absence of all manifestation is reached.
Again, after a period, the whole thing is disturbed,
projected outward, again it slowly
comes out in the form of waves; for all motion
in this universe is in the form of waves, successive
rise and fall.</p>

<p>Some of these old philosophers taught that
the whole universe quiets down for a period;
others maintained that this quieting down applies
only to systems. That is to say, that while
our system here, this solar system, will quiet
down and go back into that undifferentiated
state, there are millions of other systems going
the other way. I should rather follow the
second opinion, that this quieting down is not
simultaneous over the whole universe, but that
in different parts different things are going on.
But the principle remains the same, that all
that we see, that Nature herself is progressing
in successive rises and falls. The one stage,
going back to the balance, to the perfect equilibrium,
is called the end of a cycle. The whole
<i>Kalpa</i>, the evolution and the involution, has
been compared by theistic writers in India to
the inbreathing and outbreathing of God; God,
as it were, breathes out the universe, and it
returns into Him again. When it quiets down,
what becomes of the universe? It still exists,
only in finer form, as it is called in Sanskrit,
in the “causal state” (<i>Kârana Sarira</i>). Causation,
time and space are still there, only they
are potential. This return to an undifferentiated
condition constitutes involution. Involution
and evolution are eternally going on, so
that when we speak of a beginning, we refer
only to the beginning of a cycle.</p>

<p>The most extraneous part of the universe is
what in modern times we call gross matter.
The ancient Hindus called it the <i>Bhutas</i>, the
external elements. There is one element which
according to them is eternal; every other element
is produced out of this one, and this
eternal element is called <i>Âkâsa</i>. It is somewhat
similar to the modern idea of ether,
though not exactly the same. This is the
primal element out of which everything proceeds,
and along with this element there was
something called <i>Prâna</i>: we shall see what it
is as we go on. This <i>prâna</i> and this <i>âkâsa</i>
eternally exist, and they combine and recombine
and form all manifestation. Then at the
end of the cycle everything subsides and goes
back to the unmanifested form of <i>âkâsa</i> and
<i>prâna</i>. There is in the Rig Veda, the oldest
scriptures in existence, a beautiful passage describing
creation, and it is most poetical—“When
there was neither ought nor nought,
when darkness was rolling over darkness, what
existed?” and the answer is given, “It (the
Eternal One) then existed without motion.”
<i>Prâna</i> and <i>âkâsa</i> were latent in that Eternal
One, but there was no phenomenal manifestation.
This state is called <i>Avyaktam</i>, which
literally means “without vibration,” or unmanifested.
At the beginning of a new cycle
of evolution, this <i>avyaktam</i> begins to vibrate
and blow after blow is given by <i>prâna</i> to the
<i>âkâsa</i>. This causes condensation and gradually,
through the forces of attraction and repulsion,
atoms are formed. These in turn
condense into molecules and finally into the
different elements of Nature.</p>

<p>We generally find these things very curiously
translated; people do not go to the ancient
philosophers or to their commentators for their
translation and have not learning enough to
understand for themselves. They translate the
elements as “air,” “fire,” and so on. If they
would go to the commentators they would find
that they do not mean anything of the sort.
The <i>âkâsa</i>, made to vibrate by the repeated
blows of <i>prâna</i>, produces <i>vâyu</i> or the vibratory
state of the <i>âkâsa</i>, which in turn produces
gaseous matter. The vibrations growing more
and more rapid generate heat, which in Sanskrit
is called <i>tejas</i>. Gradually it is cooled off and
the gaseous substance becomes solid, <i>prithivi</i>.
We had first <i>âkâsa</i>, then came heat, then it
became liquified, and when still more condensed
appeared as solid matter. It goes back to the
unmanifested condition in exactly the reverse
way. The solids will be converted into liquid
and the liquid into a mass of heat, that will
slowly go back into the gaseous state, disintegration
of atoms will begin, finally equilibrium
of all forces will be reached, vibration
will stop and the cycle of evolution which in
Sanskrit is called <i>Kalpa</i> is at an end. We
know from modern astronomy that this earth
and sun of ours are undergoing the same transitions,
this solid earth will melt down and
become liquid once more, and will eventually
go back to the gaseous state.</p>

<p><i>Prâna</i> cannot work alone without the help
of <i>âkâsa</i>. All that we know is that motion
or vibration and every movement that we see
is a modification of this <i>prâna</i>, and everything
that we know in the form of matter, either as
form or as resistance, is a modification of this
<i>âkâsa</i>. This <i>prâna</i> cannot exist alone, or act
without a medium, but in every state of it,
whether as pure <i>prâna</i>, or when it changes into
other forces of nature, say gravitation or centrifugal
attraction, it can never be separate
from <i>âkâsa</i>. You have never seen force without
matter or matter without force; what we
call force and matter being simply the gross
manifestations of these same things, which,
when superfine, we call <i>prâna</i> and <i>âkâsa</i>.
<i>Prâna</i> you can call in English the life, or vital
energy, but you must not restrict it to the life
of man, nor should you identify it with the
spirit, <i>Âtman</i>. Creation is without beginning
and without end; it cannot have either, it is
an eternal on-going.</p>

<p>The next question that comes is rather a
fine one. Some European philosophers have
asserted that this world exists because “I”
exist, and if “I” do not exist, the world will
not exist. Sometimes it is expressed in this
way; they say, if all the people in the world
were to die, and there were no more human
beings, and no animals with powers of perception
and intelligence, all manifestations
would disappear. It seems paradoxical, but
gradually we shall see clearly that this can be
proved. But these European philosophers do
not know the psychology of it, although they
know the principle; modern philosophy has got
only a glimpse of it.</p>

<p>First we will take another proposition of
these old psychologists which is rather startling,
that the grossest elements are the <i>bhutas</i>,
but that all gross things are the results of fine
ones. Everything that is gross is composed
of a combination of minute things, so the
<i>bhutas</i> must be composed of certain fine particles,
called in Sanskrit the <i>tanmâtras</i>. I
smell a flower; to smell that, something must
come in contact with my nose; the flower is
there and I do not see it move towards me;
but without something coming in contact with
my nose I cannot smell the flower. That which
comes from the flower and into contact with
my nose are the <i>tanmâtras</i>, fine molecules of
that flower, so fine that no diminution can be
perceived in the flower. So with heat, light,
sight, and everything. These <i>tanmâtras</i> can
again be subdivided into atoms. Different
philosophers have different theories, and we
know these are only theories, so we leave them
out of discussion. Sufficient for us that everything
gross is composed of things that are very,
very minute. We first get the gross elements,
which we feel externally, and composing them
are the fine elements, which our organs touch,
which come in contact with the nerves of the
nose, eyes and ears. That ethereal wave which
touches my eyes, I cannot see, yet I know it must
come in contact with my optic nerve before I can
see the light. So with hearing, we can never
see the particles that come in contact with our
ears, but we know that they must be there.
What is the cause of these <i>tanmâtras</i>? A very
startling and curious answer is given by our
psychologists,—self-consciousness. That is the
cause of these fine materials, and the cause of
the organs. What are these organs? Here is
first the eye, but the eye does not see. If the
eyes did see, when a man is dead, and his eyes
are still perfect, they would still be able to see.
There is some change somewhere; something
has gone out of the man, and that something,
which really sees, of which the eye is the instrument,
is called the organ. So this nose is
an instrument, and there is an organ corresponding
to it. Modern physiology can tell
you what that is, a nerve centre in the brain.
The eyes, ears, etc., are simply the external
instruments. It may be said that the organs,
<i>Indriyas</i>, as they are called in Sanskrit, are
the real seats of perception.</p>

<p>What is the use of having one organ for the
nose, and one for the eyes, and so on? Why
will not one serve the purpose? To make it
clear to you,—I am talking, and you are listening,
and you do not see what is going on
around you because the mind has attached
itself to the organ of hearing, and has detached
itself from the sight organ. If there were only
one organ the mind would hear and see at the
same time, it would see and hear and smell at
the same time, and it would be impossible for it
not to do all three at the same time. Therefore
it is necessary that there should be separate
organs for all these centres. This has
been borne out by modern physiology. It is
certainly possible for us to see and hear at
the same time, but that is because the mind
attaches itself partially to both centres, which
are the organs. What are the instruments?
We see that these are really made of the gross
materials. Here they are,—eyes, nose, and
ears, etc. What are the organs? They are
also made of materials, because they are
centres. Just as this body is composed of gross
material for transforming <i>prâna</i> into different
gross forces, so these finer organs behind, are
composed of the fine elements, for the manufacture
of <i>prâna</i> into the finer forces of perception
and all kindred things. All these
organs or <i>indriyas</i> combined, plus the internal
instrument or <i>antahkarana</i>, are called the finer
body of man,—the <i>linga</i> (or <i>sûkshma</i>) <i>sarira</i>.</p>

<p>It has a real form, because everything material
must have a form. Behind the <i>indriyas</i>
is what is called the <i>manas</i>, the <i>chitta</i> in <i>vritti</i>,
what might be called the vibratory state of the
mind, the unsettled state. If you throw a stone
into a calm lake, first there will be vibration,
and then resistance. For a moment the water
will vibrate and then it will react on the stone.
So, when any impression comes on the <i>chitta</i>,
or “mind stuff,” it vibrates a little. This state
of the mind is called the <i>manas</i>. Then comes
the reaction, the will. There is another thing
behind this will which accompanies all the acts
of the mind, which is called egoism, the
<i>ahamkâra</i>, the self-consciousness, which says
“I am,” and behind that is what is called
<i>Buddhi</i>, the intellect, the highest form of nature’s
existence. Behind the intellect is the
true Self of man, the <i>Purusha</i>, the pure, the
perfect, who is alone the seer, and for whom
is all this change. The Purusha is looking on
at all these changes; he himself is never impure;
but by implication, what the Vedantists call
<i>adhyâsam</i>, by reflection, he appears to be impure.
It is like a red flower held before a piece
of crystal; the crystal will look red; or a blue
flower and the crystal will look blue; and yet
the crystal itself is colorless. We will take
for granted that there are many selves; each
self is pure and perfect, but it is all these
various divisions of gross matter and fine
matter that are imposing on the self, and making
it variously colored. Why is nature doing
all this? Nature is undergoing all these
changes for the improvement of the soul; all
this creation is for the benefit of the soul, so
that it may be free. This immense book
which we call the universe is stretched before
man so that he may read, and come out, as an
omniscient and omnipotent being. I must here
tell you that some of our best psychologists
do not believe in a personal God in the sense
in which you believe in Him. The real father
of our psychologists, Kapila, denies the existence
of God as a Creator. His idea is that a
personal God is quite unnecessary; Nature itself
is sufficient to work out all that is good. What
is called the “Design” theory he repudiated,
and said a more childish theory was never
advanced. But he admits a peculiar kind of
God; he says we are all struggling to get free,
and when man becomes free he can, as it were,
melt away into Nature for the time being, only
to come out at the beginning of the next cycle
and be its ruler; come out an omniscient and
omnipotent being. In that sense he can be
called God; you and I and the humblest beings
will be gods in different cycles. Kapila says
such a God will be temporal, but an eternal
God, eternally omnipotent and eternally ruler
of the universe, cannot be. If there were such
a God, there would be this difficulty: he must
either be bound or free. A God who is perfectly
free would not create; there would be no
necessity. If he were bound, he would not
create because he could not, he would be weak
himself. So, in either case, there cannot be
an omnipotent or omniscient eternal ruler. So
wherever the word God is mentioned in our
Scriptures, Kapila says it means those perfected
souls who have become free. The
<i>Sânkhya</i> system does not believe in the unity
of all souls. Vedânta believes that all individual
souls are united in one cosmic Being
called <i>Brahman</i>, but Kapila, the founder of the
<i>Sânkhya</i>, was dualistic. His analysis of the
universe so far as it goes is really marvellous.
He was the father of Hindu evolutionists, and
all the later philosophical systems are simply
outcomes of his thought.</p>

<p>According to this system all souls will regain
their freedom and their natural rights, which
are omnipotence and omniscience. Here the
question may be asked, whence is this bondage
of the souls? The <i>Sânkhya</i> says it is without
beginning, but if it be without beginning it
must also be without end, and we shall never
be free. Kapila explains that this “without
beginning” means not in a constant line. Nature
is without beginning and without end, but
not in the same sense as is the soul, because
Nature has no individuality, just as a river
flowing by us is every moment getting a fresh
body of water, and the sum total of all these
bodies of water is the river, so the river is not
a constant quantity. Similarly everything in
Nature is constantly changing, but the soul
never changes. Therefore as Nature is always
changing, it is possible for the soul to come
out of its bondage. One theory of the <i>Sânkhya</i>
is peculiar to this psychology. The whole
of the universe is built upon the same plan as
one single man, or one little being; so, just as
I have a mind, there is also a cosmic mind.
When this macrocosm evolves there must be
first intelligence, then egoism, then the <i>tanmâtras</i>
and the organs, and then the gross elements.
The whole universe according to
Kapila is one body, all that we see are the
grosser bodies, and behind these are the finer
bodies, and behind them, a universal egoism,
and behind that a universal Intelligence, but
all this is <i>in</i> Nature, all this is manifestation of
Nature, not outside of Nature. Each one of
us is a part of that cosmic consciousness. There
is a sum-total of intelligence out of which we
draw what we require, so there is a sum-total
of mental force in the universe out of which
we are drawing eternally, but the seed for the
body must come from the parents. The theory
includes heredity and reincarnation too. The
material is given to the soul out of which to
manufacture a body, but that material is given
by hereditary transmission from the parents.</p>

<p>We come now to that proposition that in this
process there is an involution and an evolution.
All is evolved out of that indiscreet Nature;
and then is involved again and becomes
<i>Avyaktam</i>. It is impossible, according to the
<i>Sânkhyas</i>, for any material thing to exist,
which has not as its material some portion of
consciousness. Consciousness is the material
out of which all manifestation is made. The
elucidation of this comes in our next lecture,
but I will show how it can be proved. I do
not know this table as it is, but it makes an
impression; it comes to the eyes, then to the
<i>indriyas</i>, and then to the mind; the mind then
reacts, and that reaction is what I call the
table. It is just the same as throwing a stone
into a lake; the lake throws a wave against
the stone; this wave is what we know. The
waves coming out are all we know. In the
same way the fashion of this wall is in my
mind; what is external nobody knows; when
I want to know it, it has to become that material
which I furnish; I, with my own mind,
have furnished the material for my eyes, and
the something which is outside is only the
occasion, the suggestion, and upon that suggestion
I project my mind, and it takes the
form of what I see. The question is, how do
we all see the same things? Because we all
have a part of this cosmic mind. Those who
have mind will see the thing, and those who
have not will not see it. This goes to show
that since this universe has existed there has
never been a want of mind, of that one cosmic
mind. Every human being, every animal, is
also furnished out of that cosmic mind, because
it is always present and furnishing
material for their formation.</p>
</chapter>
