<document uuid="CD7IBDNpyRoKwr2rrFwV4">
<meta>
<copyright>CC0/PD. No rights reserved</copyright>
<source url="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/edith-wharton/hudson-river-bracketed">Standard Ebooks</source>
<title n="XXVII"/>
</meta>
<chapter>
<p>Laura LouвАЩs convalescence was slow, her illness expensive. Upton, appealed to by Mrs. Tracy, said all his savings had gone into buying a Ford, and he could do nothing for them for the present. Vance knew that his mother-in-law expected his family to come to his aid. She ascribed Laura LouвАЩs illness to his imprudence, and felt that, since his endless scribbling brought in so little, he ought to get help from home. But Vance could not bring himself to ask for money, and his reports of Laura LouвАЩs illness produced only letters of sympathy from his mother and grandmother, and knitted bed jackets from the girls. His father wrote that times were bad in real estate, and offered again to try and get him a job on the <i>Free Speaker</i> if he would come back to live at Euphoria. And there the matter ended.</p>
<p>At odds with himself, he ground out a dull article on вАЬThe New Poetry,вАЭ the result of random reading among the works of the Coconut Tree poets; but it satisfied neither him nor the poets. He tried to make a plan for <i>Loot</i>, but it crumbled to nothing. He was too ignorant of that tumultuous metropolitan world to picture it except through other eyes. If he could have lived in it for a while, if somebody like Mrs. Tarrant had let him into its secrets, perhaps he could have made a book of it; but anything he did unaided would have to be borrowed from other books. Besides, he did not want to denounce or to show up, as most of the вАЬsocietyвАЭ novelists did, but to take apart the works of the machine, and find out what all those people behind the splendid house fronts signified in the general scheme of things. Until he understood that, he couldnвАЩt write about them. He brought his difficulty to Eric Rauch. вАЬUnless I can think their thoughts itвАЩs no use,вАЭ he said. Rauch looked puzzled, and seemed to regard the difficulty as an imaginary one. вАЬFunny to me you canвАЩt get hold of a subject,вАЭ he said; and Vance rejoined: вАЬOh, but I canвБ†вАФhundreds; they swarm. Only theyвАЩre all subjects I donвАЩt know enough about to tackle them.вАЭ вАЬWell, I guess youвАЩre in the doldrums,вАЭ Rauch commented; and the talk ended.</p>
<p>One day someone related in VanceвАЩs presence a tragic episode which had happened in a group of strolling actors. The picturesqueness of it seized on his imagination, and he tried to bring it to life; but here again he lacked familiarity with the conditions, and his ardour flagged. Fellows at the Coconut Tree talked a lot about working up a subject, about documentation and so forth; but Vance obscurely felt that he could not go out on purpose to hunt for local colour, and that inspiration must come to him in other ways. Perhaps a talk with a man like Tristram Fynes would given him his clue. He wrote and asked Fynes for an appointment; but he received no answer to his letter.</p>
<p>Mrs. Pulsifer did write again. She asked why he hadnвАЩt been back to see her, and suggested his coming to dine, giving him the choice of two evenings. The letter reached him on the day when he had taken his watch and his evening clothes to a pawnbroker. He wrote that he couldnвАЩt come to dine, but would call some afternoon; and she wired naming the next day. When he presented himself he found the great drawing rooms empty, and while he waited he wandered from one to another, gazing and dreaming. Art had hitherto figured in his mind as something apart from life, inapplicable to its daily uses; something classified, catalogued, and buried in museums. Here for the first time it became a breathing presence, he saw its relation to life, and caught a glimpse of the use of riches and leisureвБ†вАФadvanced even to the assumption that it might be the task of one class to have these things and preserve them, to live like a priestly caste isolated for the purpose. The stuffed dove on the gilt basket, he thought, reverting again to his old symbol of the mysterious utility of the useless.вБ† вБ†вА¶ Mrs. PulsiferвАЩs arrival interrupted his musings, and gave him a surprised sense of the incongruity between the treasures and their custodian.</p>
<p>She looked worried and excited; drew him at once into the circular sitting room, and impetuously accused him of being sorry sheвАЩd come back, because now heвАЩd have to talk to her instead of looking at the pictures. Vance had no conversational parries; he could only have kissed her or questioned her about her possessions; the latter course he saw would be displeasing, and he felt no temptation to the former, for she had a cold, and her face, in the spring light, looked sallow and elderly. вАЬI do like wandering about this house first-rate,вАЭ he confessed.</p>
<p>вАЬWell, then, why donвАЩt you come oftener? I know IвАЩm not clever; I canвАЩt talk to you; but if youвАЩd come and dine IвАЩd have just a few of the right people; brilliant peopleвБ†вАФFrenside, and Lewis and Halo Tarrant, and Sibelius, from the Metropolitan, whoвАЩd tell you ever so much more than I can about my pictures.вАЭ She became pathetic in her self-effacement, and when she repeated: вАЬWhy wonвАЩt you come? Why do you always refuse?вАЭ he lost his head, and stammered: вАЬIвБ† вБ†вА¶ no.вБ† вБ†вА¶ I canвАЩtвБ†вАФI canвАЩt dine with you.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYou mean youвАЩve got more amusing things to do?вАЭ she insinuated; and he answered: вАЬLord, no, not that. ItвАЩsвБ†вАФIвАЩm too poor,вАЭ he finally blurted out.</p>
<p>There was a silence.</p>
<p>вАЬToo poorвБ†вАФ?вАЭ she echoed, with an uncomprehending look.</p>
<p>He laughed. вАЬFor one thing IвАЩve got no evening clothes. IвАЩve had to pawn them.вАЭ</p>
<p>Mrs. Pulsifer, who was sitting near him, and leaning forward in her solicitous way, involuntarily drew back. вАЬOhвБ†вАФвАЭ she faltered, and he divined that her embarrassment was greater than his. The discovery somehow put him at his ease.</p>
<p>вАЬOh, you donвАЩt need to look so frightened. ItвАЩs a thing that happens to people,вАЭ he joked. She murmured: вАЬIвАЩm so sorry,вАЭ and her lips seemed shaping themselves for the expression of further sympathy. She leaned nearer again, and he saw she was feverishly wondering what she ought to say. Her helplessness touched him; in her place he would have known so well! She seemed a creature whose impulses of pity had become atrophied, and who was vainly trying to give him a sign of human feeling across the desert waste of her vast possessions. вАЬIвАЩm so sorry,вАЭ she began again, in a whisper, as if her voice was unable to bridge the distance. Vance stood up and took a few steps across the room. If she <em>was</em> sorry, reallyвБ†вАФas sorry as all that.вБ† вБ†вА¶ He stopped in front of her, and began to speak in a low confused voice. вАЬFact is, IвАЩm down and outвБ†вАФoh just temporarily, of course; IвАЩve had unexpected expenses.вБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ He paused, wondering desperately why he had ever begun. Mrs. Pulsifer sat before him without moving. Even her eyes were motionless, and her startled hands. He wondered if no one had ever spoken to her of such a thing as poverty. вАЬLook here,вАЭ he broke out, вАЬif you really believe in me, will you lend me two thousand dollars?вАЭ</p>
<p>His question echoed through the room as if he had shouted it. A slight tremor passed over Mrs. PulsiferвАЩs face; then her immobility became rigid. The situation clearly had no parallel in her experience, and she felt herself pitifully unequal to it. The fact exasperated Vance. It was all wrong that these people, the chosen custodians of knowledge and beauty, should be so stupid, so unfitted for their task. He hung before her irresolute, angry with himself and her. вАЬIвАЩd better go,вАЭ he muttered at length.</p>
<p>She looked up, disconcerted. вАЬOh, noвБ† вБ†вА¶ please donвАЩt. IвАЩm so sorry.вБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ</p>
<p>The meaningless repetition irritated him. вАЬI donвАЩt suppose you ever before met a fellow who was dead broke, did you? I suppose that young man who opens the door has orders not to let them in,вАЭ he jeered, flushed with his own humiliation.</p>
<p>She grew pale, and her hands moved uneasily. вАЬIвБ†вАФoh, you donвАЩt understand; you donвАЩt. I try toвБ† вБ†вА¶ to live up to my responsibilities.вБ† вБ†вА¶ These thingsвБ† вБ†вА¶ I have advisersвБ† вБ†вА¶ a most efficient staff who deal with them.вБ† вБ†вА¶ Every case isвБ†вАФis conscientiously investigated.вАЭ She seemed to be quoting a social service report.</p>
<p>вАЬOh, IвАЩm not a case,вАЭ Vance interrupted drily. вАЬI thought you acted as if you wanted me for a friendвБ†вАФthatвАЩs all.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI didвБ†вАФI do. I only mean.вБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ She lifted horrified eyes to his. вАЬYou see, thereвАЩs the prize.вБ† вБ†вА¶ If anyone knew thatвБ† вБ†вА¶ that youвАЩd come to me for assistanceвБ† вБ†вА¶ that I.вБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬOh, damn the prize! Excuse me; IвАЩm sorry for my blunder. There are times when a man sees a big ditch in front of him and doesnвАЩt know how heвАЩs going to get across. IвАЩm that manвБ†вАФand I spoke without thinking.вАЭ</p>
<p>Her eyes, still on his, grew moist with tears. вАЬItвАЩs so dreadfulвБ†вАФyour being in such trouble. I had no idea.вБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ She glanced about her, almost furtively, as if the efficient staff who dealt with her вАЬcasesвАЭ might be listening behind a screen. вАЬI do want to help you if I can,вАЭ she went on, hardly above a whisper. вАЬIf youвАЩll give me time IвБ† вБ†вА¶ I think I could arrangeвБ† вБ†вА¶ but of course it would have to be quite privately.вБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ</p>
<p>He softened at the sight of her distress. вАЬYouвАЩre very kind. But I guess we wonвАЩt talk of it anymore. IвАЩve been tired and worried and I started thinking out loud.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬBut itвАЩs so wrong, so cruel, that you, with your genius, should have such worries. I donвАЩt understand.вАЭ She drew her brows together in anxious conjecture. вАЬI thought there was such a demand for what you write, and that you had a permanent job in the <i>New Hour</i>.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes, I have. But theyвАЩre just starting and canвАЩt pay much. And IвАЩm pledged to give them whatever I write. But IвАЩd have pulled through all right if other things hadnвАЩt gone wrong. And I will anyhow.вАЭ He held his hand out. вАЬYouвАЩve helped me a lot, just letting me look at those pictures. Thank you for it. Goodbye.вАЭ</p>
<p>The decision of his manner seemed to communicate itself to her, and she stood up also, pale and almost beautiful under the stress of an unknown emotion. вАЬNo, no, not goodbye, I do want to help youвБ†вАФI want you to tell me what it is thatвАЩs wrong.вБ† вБ†вА¶ I know young men are sometimes foolish.вАЭ She laid on his arm a bejewelled hand of which one ring would have bought his freedom.</p>
<p>Vance gave an impatient laugh. вАЬFoolish? Is that what you people call not having enough money to keep alive on? WhatвАЩs wrong with me is that my wifeвАЩs been desperately sickвБ† вБ†вА¶ sick for weeks. That costs.вАЭ</p>
<p>There was a silence. Mrs. PulsiferвАЩs hand slipped away. She drew back a step and slowly repeated: вАЬYour wife? You mean to say youвАЩre married?вАЭ Vance made a gesture of assent.</p>
<p>вАЬBut I donвАЩt understand. You never told me.вБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬDidnвАЩt I? Maybe I didnвАЩt.вАЭ</p>
<p>She continued to look at him uncertainly. вАЬHow could I know? I never thoughtвБ† вБ†вА¶ you never spoke.вБ† вБ†вА¶ But perhaps,вАЭ she faltered, a curious light of expectancy in her tired eyes, вАЬitвАЩs because your marriage isвБ†вАФunhappy?вАЭ</p>
<p>Vance coloured hotly. вАЬGod, no! IвАЩm only unhappy because I canвАЩt do all I want for her.вАЭ He thought afterward that he had never loved Laura Lou as he did at that moment.</p>
<p>вАЬOh.вБ† вБ†вА¶ I see.вБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ he heard Mrs. Pulsifer murmur; and he was vaguely conscious of the fading of the light from her eyes.</p>
<p>вАЬWell, goodbye,вАЭ he repeated. She seemed about to speak, to make some sign to detain him; but her narrowed lips let pass only a faint echo of his goodbye. It drifted mournfully after him as he walked down the endless perspective of tapestried and gilded emptiness to the hall below, where the tall young man in dark clothes and silver buttons was waiting with a perfectly matched twin to throw back the double doors. Vance wondered ironically whether they added to their other mysterious duties that of investigating Mrs. PulsiferвАЩs cases; but he knew that his own, at any rate, would never be brought up for examination.</p>
<hr/>
<p>One of the fellows at the Coconut Tree gave him the name of a moneylender; and a few days later he had a thousand dollars in his pocket. He told Mrs. Tracy he had enough to pay off Hayes, and asked for his address. She gave it without comment, and Vance, thankful to avoid explanations, returned to New York the next day to discharge his debt. He had no idea how he was going to meet the interest on the loan; but he put that out of his mind with the ease of an inexperienced borrower.</p>
<p>The address led to a narrow office building in an uptown street, where, across the front of an upper floor, he read: вАЬ<b>storecraft</b>,вАЭ and underneath: вАЬSupplies Taste and saves Money.вАЭ He was admitted to a small room with roughcast walls, a sham Marie Laurencin, slender marquetry chairs, and a silvered mannequin in a Spanish shawl. There he waited till a fluffy-headed girl in a sports suit introduced him to an inner office, where Bunty Hayes, throned at a desk, was explaining to another girl: вАЬChanel, six almond-green Engadines: Vionnet, duplicate order apricot charmeuse pyjamas.вБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ He broke off and sat staring. вАЬPatou, six pastel-blue RivierasвБ†вАФвАЭ he went on automatically; then, with a change of tone: вАЬAll right, Gladys; weвАЩll finish up later.вАЭ The girl vanished, and he turned to Vance. вАЬSay, I didnвАЩt see it was you, first off.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬMaybe youвАЩre too busy,вАЭ Vance began.</p>
<p>вАЬNo, but I was expecting a fellow with a new style of bust-restrainer. Never mind; sit down.вАЭ He pushed a chair forward. His manner was curt and businesslike, but not unfriendly; and Vance felt less at ease than if he had not been met with anathemas.</p>
<p>вАЬYouвАЩre on a new job,вАЭ he said tentatively.</p>
<p>Bunty Hayes leaned back, swung around in his swivel chair, and thrust out his legs, displaying perfectly creased trousers. He had grown stouter, and had large yellow horn spectacles and carefully varnished hair. вАЬWhy, yes,вАЭ he said. вАЬFact is, thereвАЩs more in it. Folks want to tour in the holidays; but they want to shop all the year round, and they all want to shop in New York. Hundred and fifty million of вАЩem do. StorecraftвАЩs the answer to that. Here: seen one of our cards? WeвАЩre going to move to Fifth Avenue next year. If you want to <em>do</em> big, you got to <em>see</em> big. ThatвАЩs my motto. See here, now; you live in the suburbs: well, weвАЩre the commuterвАЩs Providence. Supply you with everything you like, from your marketing to a picture gallery. WeвАЩre going to have an art guild next year: buy your old masters for you, and all you got to do is to drive the hooks into your parlour wall and invite the neighbours.вАЭ</p>
<p>Vance had not seated himself. He drew out the money and laid it on the desk. вАЬHereвАЩs what we owe you,вАЭ he said.</p>
<p>вАЬOh, hellвБ†вАФвАЭ said Hayes. The two men faced each other uneasily. At length Hayes nodded and said: вАЬAвАЩright,вАЭ and put his hand out toward the money. вАЬWhoвАЩll I make the receipt out to?вАЭ he asked, evidently not knowing what to say next. Vance said to Mrs. Tracy, and stood with his hands in his pockets leaning against the door. Hayes wrote the receipt rapidly, blotted and handed it to Vance. вАЬWell, thatвАЩs over,вАЭ he remarked with an attempt at ease. Vance put the paper in his pocket. As he was turning to go Hayes stood up, and began, in an embarrassed voice: вАЬSee hereвБ†вАФвАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬIвБ†вАФyour wife was sick when I called the other day. I was real sorry. Wish youвАЩd tell her.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬSure,вАЭ said Vance, nodding and swinging out of the door. On the stairs, it came over him that he had behaved like an oaf, and he was half minded to turn back and tell HayesвБ†вАФTell him what? He didnвАЩt know. But he vaguely felt there was a score between them which the money, after all, hadnвАЩt wiped out.вБ† вБ†вА¶</p>
<hr/>
<p>He had never yet spoken to Laura Lou about Hayes. On his return that evening, when he went to her room, he made up his mind to do so. The room looked pleasant. There was a fire in the stove and a bunch of spring flowers on the table. Laura LouвАЩs bed was neatly made, and she lay on the old steamer chair which he had brought up from the porch. Mrs. Tracy was below, preparing supper, and the house, sometimes so dreary and repellent to him, seemed peaceful and homelike. Laura LouвАЩs face lit up at his entrance. вАЬHereвБ†вАФI brought you these. TheyвАЩre good and juicy,вАЭ he said, pulling a couple of oranges out of his overcoat pockets. He bent to kiss her, and she pressed her cheek against his. вАЬOh, theyвАЩre beauties, Vanney; but you oughtnвАЩt to have spent all that money.вАЭ</p>
<p>He sat down beside her, laughed, and said: вАЬIвАЩve spent a lot more; IвАЩve paid off what was owing to Hayes.вАЭ</p>
<p>She flushed a tender rose colour. вАЬOh, Vanny! The whole of it? IsnвАЩt that great?вАЭ Her hands tightened in his. вАЬMotherвАЩll be crazy glad. But itвАЩs such a lot of money; how in the world did you manage?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬOh IвБ† вБ†вА¶ I fixed it up. It was easy enough. I got an advance.вАЭ</p>
<p>The vague answer seemed to satisfy her, and she rested her head against his shoulder and stroked the oranges with her free hand. вАЬWell, thatвАЩs just great. I guess they must think the world of you at the office,вАЭ she said placidly.</p>
<p>Vance held her to him. After a pause he said: вАЬI always felt sorry for the fellow, somehow.вАЭ</p>
<p>Through her deep lashes she looked up, as though wondering a little. вАЬWell, you donвАЩt have to any longer, do you?вАЭ</p>
<p>Vance felt as if she had moved away from him; but in reality her light body was pressed more closely to his. вАЬWhy, I donвАЩt know,вАЭ he said, вАЬI guess we didnвАЩt act any too square to him, apart from the money. I wish now weвАЩd given him warningвБ† вБ†вА¶ or somethingвБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ</p>
<p>She gave a little wriggle of contentment. вАЬWell, yes, I wish we had too; but I guess it was safer, the way we did it.вАЭ For her, at least, the old score had been completely wiped out. He wondered, as he clasped her, if anyone would ever feel about the deep invisible things as he did.</p>
<p>To stifle conjecture he bent down and kissed her lids shut, one after the other. That funny lonely woman in the big house, who had imagined he was unhappily marriedвБ† вБ†вА¶ !</p>
<p>Next morning the expressman deposited at the door a big basket with the вАЬStorecraftвАЭ label, full of perfumed grapefruit and polished mandarins and boxes of Californian delicacies.</p>
</chapter>
</document>