<document uuid="CD7Ij5pbgOtSIlzK2ia4S">
<meta>
<copyright>CC0/PD. No rights reserved</copyright>
<source url="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/thomas-hardy/jude-the-obscure">Standard Ebooks</source>
<title n="IX"/>
</meta>
<chapter>
<p>On the platform stood Arabella. She looked him up and down.</p>
<p>вАЬYouвАЩve been to see her?вАЭ she asked.</p>
<p>вАЬI have,вАЭ said Jude, literally tottering with cold and lassitude.</p>
<p>вАЬWell, now youвАЩd best march along home.вАЭ</p>
<p>The water ran out of him as he went, and he was compelled to lean against the wall to support himself while coughing.</p>
<p>вАЬYouвАЩve done for yourself by this, young man,вАЭ said she. вАЬI donвАЩt know whether you know it.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬOf course I do. I meant to do for myself.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWhatвБ†вАФto commit suicide?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬCertainly.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWell, IвАЩm blest! Kill yourself for a woman.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬListen to me, Arabella. You think you are the stronger; and so you are, in a physical sense, now. You could push me over like a ninepin. You did not send that letter the other day, and I could not resent your conduct. But I am not so weak in another way as you think. I made up my mind that a man confined to his room by inflammation of the lungs, a fellow who had only two wishes left in the world, to see a particular woman, and then to die, could neatly accomplish those two wishes at one stroke by taking this journey in the rain. That IвАЩve done. I have seen her for the last time, and IвАЩve finished myselfвБ†вАФput an end to a feverish life which ought never to have been begun!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬLordвБ†вАФyou do talk lofty! WonвАЩt you have something warm to drink?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬNo thank you. LetвАЩs get home.вАЭ</p>
<p>They went along by the silent colleges, and Jude kept stopping.</p>
<p>вАЬWhat are you looking at?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬStupid fancies. I see, in a way, those spirits of the dead again, on this my last walk, that I saw when I first walked here!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWhat a curious chap you are!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI seem to see them, and almost hear them rustling. But I donвАЩt revere all of them as I did then. I donвАЩt believe in half of them. The theologians, the apologists, and their kin the metaphysicians, the high-handed statesmen, and others, no longer interest me. All that has been spoilt for me by the grind of stern reality!вАЭ</p>
<p>The expression of JudeвАЩs corpse-like face in the watery lamplight was indeed as if he saw people where there was nobody. At moments he stood still by an archway, like one watching a figure walk out; then he would look at a window like one discerning a familiar face behind it. He seemed to hear voices, whose words he repeated as if to gather their meaning.</p>
<p>вАЬThey seem laughing at me!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWho?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬOвБ†вАФI was talking to myself! The phantoms all about here, in the college archways, and windows. They used to look friendly in the old days, particularly Addison, and Gibbon, and Johnson, and Dr. Browne, and Bishop KenвБ†вАФвАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬCome along do! Phantoms! ThereвАЩs neither living nor dead hereabouts except a damn policeman! I never saw the streets emptier.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬFancy! The Poet of Liberty used to walk here, and the great Dissector of Melancholy there!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI donвАЩt want to hear about вАЩem! They bore me.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWalter Raleigh is beckoning to me from that laneвБ†вАФWycliffeвБ†вАФHarveyвБ†вАФHookerвБ†вАФArnoldвБ†вАФand a whole crowd of Tractarian ShadesвБ†вАФвАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI <em>donвАЩt want</em> to know their names, I tell you! What do I care about folk dead and gone? Upon my soul you are more sober when youвАЩve been drinking than when you have not!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI must rest a moment,вАЭ he said; and as he paused, holding to the railings, he measured with his eye the height of a college front. вАЬThis is old Rubric. And that Sarcophagus; and up that lane Crozier and Tudor: and all down there is Cardinal with its long front, and its windows with lifted eyebrows, representing the polite surprise of the University at the efforts of such as I.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬCome along, and IвАЩll treat you!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬVery well. It will help me home, for I feel the chilly fog from the meadows of Cardinal as if death-claws were grabbing me through and through. As Antigone said, I am neither a dweller among men nor ghosts. But, Arabella, when I am dead, youвАЩll see my spirit flitting up and down here among these!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬPooh! You maynвАЩt die after all. You are tough enough yet, old man.вАЭ</p>
<hr/>
<p>It was night at Marygreen, and the rain of the afternoon showed no sign of abatement. About the time at which Jude and Arabella were walking the streets of Christminster homeward, the Widow Edlin crossed the green, and opened the back door of the schoolmasterвАЩs dwelling, which she often did now before bedtime, to assist Sue in putting things away.</p>
<p>Sue was muddling helplessly in the kitchen, for she was not a good housewife, though she tried to be, and grew impatient of domestic details.</p>
<p>вАЬLord love вАЩee, what do ye do that yourself for, when IвАЩve come oвАЩ purpose! You knew I should come.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬOвБ†вАФI donвАЩt knowвБ†вАФI forgot! No, I didnвАЩt forget. I did it to discipline myself. I have scrubbed the stairs since eight oвАЩclock. I <em>must</em> practise myself in my household duties. IвАЩve shamefully neglected them!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWhy should ye? HeвАЩll get a better school, perhaps be a parson, in time, and youвАЩll keep two servants. вАЩTis a pity to spoil them pretty hands.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬDonвАЩt talk of my pretty hands, Mrs. Edlin. This pretty body of mine has been the ruin of me already!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬPshooвБ†вАФyouвАЩve got no body to speak of! You put me more in mind of a sperrit. But there seems something wrong tonight, my dear. Husband cross?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬNo. He never is. HeвАЩs gone to bed early.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬThen what is it?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI cannot tell you. I have done wrong today. And I want to eradicate it.вБ† вБ†вА¶ WellвБ†вАФI will tell you thisвБ†вАФJude has been here this afternoon, and I find I still love himвБ†вАФO, grossly! I cannot tell you more.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬAh!вАЭ said the widow. вАЬI told вАЩee how вАЩtwould be!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬBut it shanвАЩt be! I have not told my husband of his visit; it is not necessary to trouble him about it, as I never mean to see Jude any more. But I am going to make my conscience right on my duty to RichardвБ†вАФby doing a penanceвБ†вАФthe ultimate thing. I must!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI wouldnвАЩtвБ†вАФsince he agrees to it being otherwise, and it has gone on three months very well as it is.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYesвБ†вАФhe agrees to my living as I choose; but I feel it is an indulgence I ought not to exact from him. It ought not to have been accepted by me. To reverse it will be terribleвБ†вАФbut I must be more just to him. O why was I so unheroic!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWhat is it you donвАЩt like in him?вАЭ asked Mrs. Edlin curiously.</p>
<p>вАЬI cannot tell you. It is somethingвБ† вБ†вА¶ I cannot say. The mournful thing is, that nobody would admit it as a reason for feeling as I do; so that no excuse is left me.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬDid you ever tell Jude what it was?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬNever.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬIвАЩve heard strange tales oвАЩ husbands in my time,вАЭ observed the widow in a lowered voice. вАЬThey say that when the saints were upon the earth devils used to take husbandsвАЩ forms oвАЩ nights, and get poor women into all sorts of trouble. But I donвАЩt know why that should come into my head, for it is only a tale.вБ† вБ†вА¶ What a wind and rain it is tonight! WellвБ†вАФdonвАЩt be in a hurry to alter things, my dear. Think it over.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬNo, no! IвАЩve screwed my weak soul up to treating him more courteouslyвБ†вАФand it must be nowвБ†вАФat onceвБ†вАФbefore I break down!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI donвАЩt think you ought to force your nature. No woman ought to be expected to.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬIt is my duty. I will drink my cup to the dregs!вАЭ</p>
<p>Half-an-hour later when Mrs. Edlin put on her bonnet and shawl to leave, Sue seemed to be seized with vague terror.</p>
<p>вАЬNo, noвБ†вАФdonвАЩt go, Mrs. Edlin,вАЭ she implored, her eyes enlarged, and with a quick nervous look over her shoulder.</p>
<p>вАЬBut it is bedtime, child.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes, butвБ†вАФthereвАЩs the little spare roomвБ†вАФmy room that was. It is quite ready. Please stay, Mrs. Edlin!вБ†вАФI shall want you in the morning.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬO wellвБ†вАФI donвАЩt mind, if you wish. Nothing will happen to my four old walls, whether I be there or no.вАЭ</p>
<p>She then fastened up the doors, and they ascended the stairs together.</p>
<p>вАЬWait here, Mrs. Edlin,вАЭ said Sue. вАЬIвАЩll go into my old room a moment by myself.вАЭ</p>
<p>Leaving the widow on the landing Sue turned to the chamber which had been hers exclusively since her arrival at Marygreen, and pushing to the door knelt down by the bed for a minute or two. She then arose, and taking her nightgown from the pillow undressed and came out to Mrs. Edlin. A man could be heard snoring in the room opposite. She wished Mrs. Edlin good night, and the widow entered the room that Sue had just vacated.</p>
<p>Sue unlatched the other chamber door, and, as if seized with faintness, sank down outside it. Getting up again she half opened the door, and said вАЬRichard.вАЭ As the word came out of her mouth she visibly shuddered.</p>
<p>The snoring had quite ceased for some time, but he did not reply. Sue seemed relieved, and hurried back to Mrs. EdlinвАЩs chamber. вАЬAre you in bed, Mrs. Edlin?вАЭ she asked.</p>
<p>вАЬNo, dear,вАЭ said the widow, opening the door. вАЬI be old and slow, and it takes me a long while to un-ray. I hanвАЩt unlaced my jumps yet.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬIвБ†вАФdonвАЩt hear him! And perhapsвБ†вАФperhapsвБ†вАФвАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWhat, child?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬPerhaps heвАЩs dead!вАЭ she gasped. вАЬAnd thenвБ†вАФI should be <em>free</em>, and I could go to Jude!вБ† вБ†вА¶ AhвБ†вАФnoвБ†вАФI forgot <em>her</em>вБ†вАФand God!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬLetвАЩs go and hearken. NoвБ†вАФheвАЩs snoring again. But the rain and the wind is so loud that you can hardly hear anything but between whiles.вАЭ</p>
<p>Sue had dragged herself back. вАЬMrs. Edlin, good night again! I am sorry I called you out.вАЭ The widow retreated a second time.</p>
<p>The strained, resigned look returned to SueвАЩs face when she was alone. вАЬI must do itвБ†вАФI must! I must drink to the dregs!вАЭ she whispered. вАЬRichard!вАЭ she said again.</p>
<p>вАЬHeyвБ†вАФwhat? Is that you, Susanna?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWhat do you want? Anything the matter? Wait a moment.вАЭ He pulled on some articles of clothing, and came to the door. вАЬYes?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWhen we were at Shaston I jumped out of the window rather than that you should come near me. I have never reversed that treatment till nowвБ†вАФwhen I have come to beg your pardon for it, and ask you to let me in.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬPerhaps you only think you ought to do this? I donвАЩt wish you to come against your impulses, as I have said.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬBut I beg to be admitted.вАЭ She waited a moment, and repeated, вАЬI beg to be admitted! I have been in errorвБ†вАФeven today. I have exceeded my rights. I did not mean to tell you, but perhaps I ought. I sinned against you this afternoon.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬHow?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI met Jude! I didnвАЩt know he was coming. AndвБ†вАФвАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWell?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI kissed him, and let him kiss me.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬOвБ†вАФthe old story!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬRichard, I didnвАЩt know we were going to kiss each other till we did!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬHow many times?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬA good many. I donвАЩt know. I am horrified to look back on it, and the least I can do after it is to come to you like this.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬComeвБ†вАФthis is pretty bad, after what IвАЩve done! Anything else to confess?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬNo.вАЭ She had been intending to say: вАЬI called him my darling Love.вАЭ But, as a contrite woman always keeps back a little, that portion of the scene remained untold. She went on: вАЬI am never going to see him any more. He spoke of some things of the past: and it overcame me. He spoke ofвБ†вАФthe children.вБ†вАФBut, as I have said, I am gladвБ†вАФalmost glad I meanвБ†вАФthat they are dead, Richard. It blots out all that life of mine!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWellвБ†вАФabout not seeing him again any more. ComeвБ†вАФyou really mean this?вАЭ There was something in PhillotsonвАЩs tone now which seemed to show that his three months of remarriage with Sue had somehow not been so satisfactory as his magnanimity or amative patience had anticipated.</p>
<p>вАЬYes, yes!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬPerhaps youвАЩll swear it on the New Testament?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI will.вАЭ</p>
<p>He went back to the room and brought out a little brown Testament. вАЬNow then: So help you God!вАЭ</p>
<p>She swore.</p>
<p>вАЬVery good!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬNow I supplicate you, Richard, to whom I belong, and whom I wish to honour and obey, as I vowed, to let me in.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬThink it over well. You know what it means. Having you back in the house was one thingвБ†вАФthis another. So think again.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI have thoughtвБ†вАФI wish this!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬThatвАЩs a complaisant spiritвБ†вАФand perhaps you are right. With a lover hanging about, a half-marriage should be completed. But I repeat my reminder this third and last time.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬIt is my wish!вБ† вБ†вА¶ O God!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWhat did you say O God for?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI donвАЩt know!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes you do! ButвБ† вБ†вА¶вАЭ He gloomily considered her thin and fragile form a moment longer as she crouched before him in her nightclothes. вАЬWell, I thought it might end like this,вАЭ he said presently. вАЬI owe you nothing, after these signs; but IвАЩll take you in at your word, and forgive you.вАЭ</p>
<p>He put his arm round her to lift her up. Sue started back.</p>
<p>вАЬWhatвАЩs the matter?вАЭ he asked, speaking for the first time sternly. вАЬYou shrink from me again?вБ†вАФjust as formerly!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬNo, RichardвБ†вАФIвБ†вАФIвБ†вАФwas not thinkingвБ†вАФвАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYou wish to come in here?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYou still bear in mind what it means?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes. It is my duty!вАЭ</p>
<p>Placing the candlestick on the chest of drawers he led her through the doorway, and lifting her bodily, kissed her. A quick look of aversion passed over her face, but clenching her teeth she uttered no cry.</p>
<p>Mrs. Edlin had by this time undressed, and was about to get into bed when she said to herself: вАЬAhвБ†вАФperhaps IвАЩd better go and see if the little thing is all right. How it do blow and rain!вАЭ</p>
<p>The widow went out on the landing, and saw that Sue had disappeared. вАЬAh! Poor soul! Weddings be funerals вАЩa bвАЩlieve nowadays. Fifty-five years ago, come Fall, since my man and I married! Times have changed since then!вАЭ</p>
</chapter>
</document>