<document uuid="CD7Ij5lbwmCAehNbRDFW8">
<meta>
<copyright>CC0/PD. No rights reserved</copyright>
<source url="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/thomas-hardy/jude-the-obscure">Standard Ebooks</source>
<title n="VII"/>
</meta>
<chapter>
<p>Arabella was preparing breakfast in the downstairs back room of this small, recently hired tenement of her fatherвАЩs. She put her head into the little pork-shop in front, and told Mr. Donn it was ready. Donn, endeavouring to look like a master pork-butcher, in a greasy blue blouse, and with a strap round his waist from which a steel dangled, came in promptly.</p>
<p>вАЬYou must mind the shop this morning,вАЭ he said casually. вАЬIвАЩve to go and get some inwards and half a pig from Lumsdon, and to call elsewhere. If you live here you must put your shoulder to the wheel, at least till I get the business started!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWell, for today I canвАЩt say.вАЭ She looked deedily into his face. вАЬIвАЩve got a prize upstairs.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬOh?вБ†вАФWhatвАЩs that?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬA husbandвБ†вАФalmost.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬNo!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes. ItвАЩs Jude. HeвАЩs come back to me.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYour old original one? Well, IвАЩm damned!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWell, I always did like him, that I will say.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬBut how does he come to be up there?вАЭ said Donn, humour-struck, and nodding to the ceiling.</p>
<p>вАЬDonвАЩt ask inconvenient questions, father. What weвАЩve to do is to keep him here till he and I areвБ†вАФas we were.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬHow was that?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬMarried.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬAh.вБ† вБ†вА¶ Well it is the rummest thing I ever heard ofвБ†вАФmarrying an old husband again, and so much new blood in the world! HeвАЩs no catch, to my thinking. IвАЩd have had a new one while I was about it.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬIt isnвАЩt rum for a woman to want her old husband back for respectability, though for a man to want his old wife backвБ†вАФwell, perhaps it is funny, rather!вАЭ And Arabella was suddenly seized with a fit of loud laughter, in which her father joined more moderately.</p>
<p>вАЬBe civil to him, and IвАЩll do the rest,вАЭ she said when she had recovered seriousness. вАЬHe told me this morning that his head ached fit to burst, and he hardly seemed to know where he was. And no wonder, considering how he mixed his drink last night. We must keep him jolly and cheerful here for a day or two, and not let him go back to his lodging. Whatever you advance IвАЩll pay back to you again. But I must go up and see how he is now, poor deary.вАЭ</p>
<p>Arabella ascended the stairs, softly opened the door of the first bedroom, and peeped in. Finding that her shorn Samson was asleep she entered to the bedside and stood regarding him. The fevered flush on his face from the debauch of the previous evening lessened the fragility of his ordinary appearance, and his long lashes, dark brows, and curly black hair and beard against the white pillow, completed the physiognomy of one whom Arabella, as a woman of rank passions, still felt it worth while to recapture, highly important to recapture as a woman straitened both in means and in reputation. Her ardent gaze seemed to affect him; his quick breathing became suspended, and he opened his eyes.</p>
<p>вАЬHow are you now, dear?вАЭ said she. вАЬIt is IвБ†вАФArabella.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬAh!вБ†вАФwhereвБ†вАФO yes, I remember! You gave me shelter.вБ† вБ†вА¶ I am strandedвБ†вАФillвБ†вАФdemoralizedвБ†вАФdamn bad! ThatвАЩs what I am!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬThen do stay there. ThereвАЩs nobody in the house but father and me, and you can rest till you are thoroughly well. IвАЩll tell them at the stone-works that you are knocked up.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI wonder what they are thinking at the lodgings!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬIвАЩll go round and explain. Perhaps you had better let me pay up, or theyвАЩll think weвАЩve run away?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes. YouвАЩll find enough money in my pocket there.вАЭ</p>
<p>Quite indifferent, and shutting his eyes because he could not bear the daylight in his throbbing eyeballs, Jude seemed to doze again. Arabella took his purse, softly left the room, and putting on her outdoor things went off to the lodgings she and he had quitted the evening before.</p>
<p>Scarcely half-an-hour had elapsed ere she reappeared round the corner, walking beside a lad wheeling a truck on which were piled all JudeвАЩs household possessions, and also the few of ArabellaвАЩs things which she had taken to the lodging for her short sojourn there. Jude was in such physical pain from his unfortunate breakdown of the previous night, and in such mental pain from the loss of Sue and from having yielded in his half-somnolent state to Arabella, that when he saw his few chattels unpacked and standing before his eyes in this strange bedroom, intermixed with womanвАЩs apparel, he scarcely considered how they had come there, or what their coming signalized.</p>
<p>вАЬNow,вАЭ said Arabella to her father downstairs, вАЬwe must keep plenty of good liquor going in the house these next few days. I know his nature, and if he once gets into that fearfully low state that he does get into sometimes, heвАЩll never do the honourable thing by me in this world, and I shall be left in the lurch. He must be kept cheerful. He has a little money in the savings-bank, and he has given me his purse to pay for anything necessary. Well, that will be the license; for I must have that ready at hand, to catch him the moment heвАЩs in the humour. You must pay for the liquor. A few friends, and a quiet convivial party would be the thing, if we could get it up. It would advertise the shop, and help me too.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬThat can be got up easy enough by anybody whoвАЩll afford victuals and drink.вБ† вБ†вА¶ Well yesвБ†вАФit would advertise the shopвБ†вАФthatвАЩs true.вАЭ</p>
<p>Three days later, when Jude had recovered somewhat from the fearful throbbing of his eyes and brain, but was still considerably confused in his mind by what had been supplied to him by Arabella during the intervalвБ†вАФto keep him jolly, as she expressed itвБ†вАФthe quiet convivial gathering suggested by her, to wind Jude up to the striking point, took place.</p>
<p>Donn had only just opened his miserable little pork and sausage shop, which had as yet scarce any customers; nevertheless that party advertised it well, and the Donns acquired a real notoriety among a certain class in Christminster who knew not the colleges, nor their works, nor their ways. Jude was asked if he could suggest any guest in addition to those named by Arabella and her father, and in a saturnine humour of perfect recklessness mentioned Uncle Joe, and Stagg, and the decayed auctioneer, and others whom he remembered as having been frequenters of the well-known tavern during his bout therein years before. He also suggested Freckles and Bower oвАЩ Bliss. Arabella took him at his word so far as the men went, but drew the line at the ladies.</p>
<p>Another man they knew, Tinker Taylor, though he lived in the same street, was not invited; but as he went homeward from a late job on the evening of the party, he had occasion to call at the shop for trotters. There were none in, but he was promised some the next morning. While making his inquiry Taylor glanced into the back room, and saw the guests sitting round, card-playing, and drinking, and otherwise enjoying themselves at DonnвАЩs expense. He went home to bed, and on his way out next morning wondered how the party went off. He thought it hardly worth while to call at the shop for his provisions at that hour, Donn and his daughter being probably not up, if they caroused late the night before. However, he found in passing that the door was open, and he could hear voices within, though the shutters of the meat-stall were not down. He went and tapped at the sitting-room door, and opened it.</p>
<p>вАЬWellвБ†вАФto be sure!вАЭ he said, astonished.</p>
<p>Hosts and guests were sitting card-playing, smoking, and talking, precisely as he had left them eleven hours earlier; the gas was burning and the curtains drawn, though it had been broad daylight for two hours out of doors.</p>
<p>вАЬYes!вАЭ cried Arabella, laughing. вАЬHere we are, just the same. We ought to be ashamed of ourselves, oughtnвАЩt we! But it is a sort of housewarming, you see; and our friends are in no hurry. Come in, Mr. Taylor, and sit down.вАЭ</p>
<p>The tinker, or rather reduced ironmonger, was nothing loth, and entered and took a seat. вАЬI shall lose a quarter, but never mind,вАЭ he said. вАЬWell, really, I could hardly believe my eyes when I looked in! It seemed as if I was flung back again into last night, all of a sudden.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬSo you are. Pour out for Mr. Taylor.вАЭ</p>
<p>He now perceived that she was sitting beside Jude, her arm being round his waist. Jude, like the rest of the company, bore on his face the signs of how deeply he had been indulging.</p>
<p>вАЬWell, weвАЩve been waiting for certain legal hours to arrive, to tell the truth,вАЭ she continued bashfully, and making her spirituous crimson look as much like a maiden blush as possible. вАЬJude and I have decided to make up matters between us by tying the knot again, as we find we canвАЩt do without one another after all. So, as a bright notion, we agreed to sit on till it was late enough, and go and do it offhand.вАЭ</p>
<p>Jude seemed to pay no great heed to what she was announcing, or indeed to anything whatever. The entrance of Taylor infused fresh spirit into the company, and they remained sitting, till Arabella whispered to her father: вАЬNow we may as well go.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬBut the parson donвАЩt know?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬYes, I told him last night that we might come between eight and nine, as there were reasons of decency for doing it as early and quiet as possible; on account of it being our second marriage, which might make people curious to look on if they knew. He highly approved.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬO very well: IвАЩm ready,вАЭ said her father, getting up and shaking himself.</p>
<p>вАЬNow, old darling,вАЭ she said to Jude. вАЬCome along, as you promised.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWhen did I promise anything?вАЭ asked he, whom she had made so tipsy by her special knowledge of that line of business as almost to have made him sober againвБ†вАФor to seem so to those who did not know him.</p>
<p>вАЬWhy!вАЭ said Arabella, affecting dismay. вАЬYouвАЩve promised to marry me several times as weвАЩve sat here tonight. These gentlemen have heard you.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI donвАЩt remember it,вАЭ said Jude doggedly. вАЬThereвАЩs only one womanвБ†вАФbut I wonвАЩt mention her in this Capharnaum!вАЭ</p>
<p>Arabella looked towards her father. вАЬNow, Mr. Fawley, be honourable,вАЭ said Donn. вАЬYou and my daughter have been living here together these three or four days, quite on the understanding that you were going to marry her. Of course I shouldnвАЩt have had such goings on in my house if I hadnвАЩt understood that. As a point of honour you must do it now.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬDonвАЩt say anything against my honour!вАЭ enjoined Jude hotly, standing up. вАЬIвАЩd marry the WвБ†вЄЇ of Babylon rather than do anything dishonourable! No reflection on you, my dear. It is a mere rhetorical figureвБ†вАФwhat they call in the books, hyperbole.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬKeep your figures for your debts to friends who shelter you,вАЭ said Donn.</p>
<p>вАЬIf I am bound in honour to marry herвБ†вАФas I suppose I amвБ†вАФthough how I came to be here with her I know no more than a dead manвБ†вАФmarry her I will, so help me God! I have never behaved dishonourably to a woman or to any living thing. I am not a man who wants to save himself at the expense of the weaker among us!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬThereвБ†вАФnever mind him, deary,вАЭ said she, putting her cheek against JudeвАЩs. вАЬCome up and wash your face, and just put yourself tidy, and off weвАЩll go. Make it up with father.вАЭ</p>
<p>They shook hands. Jude went upstairs with her, and soon came down looking tidy and calm. Arabella, too, had hastily arranged herself, and accompanied by Donn away they went.</p>
<p>вАЬDonвАЩt go,вАЭ she said to the guests at parting. вАЬIвАЩve told the little maid to get the breakfast while we are gone; and when we come back weвАЩll all have some. A good strong cup of tea will set everybody right for going home.вАЭ</p>
<hr/>
<p>When Arabella, Jude and Donn had disappeared on their matrimonial errand the assembled guests yawned themselves wider awake, and discussed the situation with great interest. Tinker Taylor, being the most sober, reasoned the most lucidly.</p>
<p>вАЬI donвАЩt wish to speak against friends,вАЭ he said. вАЬBut it do seem a rare curiosity for a couple to marry over again! If they couldnвАЩt get on the first time when their minds were limp, they wonвАЩt the second, by my reckoning.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬDo you think heвАЩll do it?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬHeвАЩs been put upon his honour by the woman, so he med.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬHeвАЩd hardly do it straight off like this. HeвАЩs got no license nor anything.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬSheвАЩs got that, bless you. DidnвАЩt you hear her say so to her father?вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWell,вАЭ said Tinker Taylor, re-lighting his pipe at the gas-jet. вАЬTake her all together, limb by limb, sheвАЩs not such a bad-looking pieceвБ†вАФparticular by candlelight. To be sure, halfpence that have been in circulation canвАЩt be expected to look like new ones from the Mint. But for a woman thatвАЩs been knocking about the four hemispheres for some time, sheвАЩs passable enough. A little bit thick in the flitch perhaps: but I like a woman that a puff oвАЩ wind wonвАЩt blow down.вАЭ</p>
<p>Their eyes followed the movements of the little girl as she spread the breakfast-cloth on the table they had been using, without wiping up the slops of the liquor. The curtains were undrawn, and the expression of the house made to look like morning. Some of the guests, however, fell asleep in their chairs. One or two went to the door, and gazed along the street more than once. Tinker Taylor was the chief of these, and after a time he came in with a leer on his face.</p>
<p>вАЬBy Gad, they are coming! I think the deedвАЩs done!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬNo,вАЭ said Uncle Joe, following him in. вАЬTake my word, he turned rusty at the last minute. They are walking in a very onusual way; and thatвАЩs the meaning of it!вАЭ</p>
<p>They waited in silence till the wedding party could be heard entering the house. First into the room came Arabella boisterously; and her face was enough to show that her strategy had succeeded.</p>
<p>вАЬMrs. Fawley, I presume?вАЭ said Tinker Taylor with mock courtesy.</p>
<p>вАЬCertainly. Mrs. Fawley again,вАЭ replied Arabella blandly, pulling off her glove and holding out her left hand. вАЬThereвАЩs the padlock, see.вБ† вБ†вА¶ Well, he was a very, nice, gentlemanly man indeed. I mean the clergyman. He said to me as gentle as a babe when all was done: вАШMrs. Fawley, I congratulate you heartily,вАЩ he says. вАШFor having heard your history, and that of your husband, I think you have both done the right and proper thing. And for your past errors as a wife, and his as a husband, I think you ought now to be forgiven by the world, as you have forgiven each other,вАЩ says he. Yes: he was a very, nice, gentlemanly man. вАШThe Church donвАЩt recognize divorce in her dogma, strictly speaking,вАЩ he says: вАШand bear in mind the words of the Service in your goings out and your comings in: What God hath joined together let no man put asunder.вАЩ Yes: he was a very nice, gentlemanly man.вБ† вБ†вА¶ But, Jude, my dear, you were enough to make a cat laugh! You walked that straight, and held yourself that steady, that one would have thought you were going вАЩprentice to a judge; though I knew you were seeing double all the time, from the way you fumbled with my finger.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI said IвАЩd do anything toвБ†вАФsave a womanвАЩs honour,вАЭ muttered Jude. вАЬAnd IвАЩve done it!вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬWell now, old deary, come along and have some breakfast.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬI wantвБ†вАФsomeвБ†вАФmore whisky,вАЭ said Jude stolidly.</p>
<p>вАЬNonsense, dear. Not now! ThereвАЩs no more left. The tea will take the muddle out of our heads, and we shall be as fresh as larks.вАЭ</p>
<p>вАЬAll right. IвАЩveвБ†вАФmarried you. She said I ought to marry you again, and I have straightway. It is true religion! HaвБ†вАФhaвБ†вАФha!вАЭ</p>
</chapter>
</document>