<document uuid="CD7IB6CwEZSqPR7uytob0">
<meta>
<copyright>CC0/PD. No rights reserved</copyright>
<source url="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/edith-wharton/the-age-of-innocence">Standard Ebooks</source>
<title n="XVII"/>
</meta>
<chapter>
<p>тАЬYour cousin the Countess called on mother while you were away,тАЭ Janey Archer announced to her brother on the evening of his return.</p>
<p>The young man, who was dining alone with his mother and sister, glanced up in surprise and saw Mrs. ArcherтАЩs gaze demurely bent on her plate. Mrs. Archer did not regard her seclusion from the world as a reason for being forgotten by it; and Newland guessed that she was slightly annoyed that he should be surprised by Madame OlenskaтАЩs visit.</p>
<p>тАЬShe had on a black velvet polonaise with jet buttons, and a tiny green monkey muff; I never saw her so stylishly dressed,тАЭ Janey continued. тАЬShe came alone, early on Sunday afternoon; luckily the fire was lit in the drawing-room. She had one of those new card-cases. She said she wanted to know us because youтАЩd been so good to her.тАЭ</p>
<p>Newland laughed. тАЬMadame Olenska always takes that tone about her friends. SheтАЩs very happy at being among her own people again.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬYes, so she told us,тАЭ said Mrs. Archer. тАЬI must say she seems thankful to be here.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬI hope you liked her, mother.тАЭ</p>
<p>Mrs. Archer drew her lips together. тАЬShe certainly lays herself out to please, even when she is calling on an old lady.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬMother doesnтАЩt think her simple,тАЭ Janey interjected, her eyes screwed upon her brotherтАЩs face.</p>
<p>тАЬItтАЩs just my old-fashioned feeling; dear May is my ideal,тАЭ said Mrs. Archer.</p>
<p>тАЬAh,тАЭ said her son, тАЬtheyтАЩre not alike.тАЭ</p>
<hr/>
<p>Archer had left St. Augustine charged with many messages for old Mrs. Mingott; and a day or two after his return to town he called on her.</p>
<p>The old lady received him with unusual warmth; she was grateful to him for persuading the Countess Olenska to give up the idea of a divorce; and when he told her that he had deserted the office without leave, and rushed down to St. Augustine simply because he wanted to see May, she gave an adipose chuckle and patted his knee with her puffball hand.</p>
<p>тАЬAh, ahтБатАФso you kicked over the traces, did you? And I suppose Augusta and Welland pulled long faces, and behaved as if the end of the world had come? But little MayтБатАФshe knew better, IтАЩll be bound?тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬI hoped she did; but after all she wouldnтАЩt agree to what IтАЩd gone down to ask for.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬWouldnтАЩt she indeed? And what was that?тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬI wanted to get her to promise that we should be married in April. WhatтАЩs the use of our wasting another year?тАЭ</p>
<p>Mrs. Manson Mingott screwed up her little mouth into a grimace of mimic prudery and twinkled at him through malicious lids. тАЬ тАШAsk Mamma,тАЩ I supposeтБатАФthe usual story. Ah, these MingottsтБатАФall alike! Born in a rut, and you canтАЩt root тАЩem out of it. When I built this house youтАЩd have thought I was moving to California! Nobody ever <em>had</em> built above Fortieth StreetтБатАФno, says I, nor above the Battery either, before Christopher Columbus discovered America. No, no; not one of them wants to be different; theyтАЩre as scared of it as the smallpox. Ah, my dear Mr. Archer, I thank my stars IтАЩm nothing but a vulgar Spicer; but thereтАЩs not one of my own children that takes after me but my little Ellen.тАЭ She broke off, still twinkling at him, and asked, with the casual irrelevance of old age: тАЬNow, why in the world didnтАЩt you marry my little Ellen?тАЭ</p>
<p>Archer laughed. тАЬFor one thing, she wasnтАЩt there to be married.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬNoтБатАФto be sure; moreтАЩs the pity. And now itтАЩs too late; her life is finished.тАЭ She spoke with the cold-blooded complacency of the aged throwing earth into the grave of young hopes. The young manтАЩs heart grew chill, and he said hurriedly: тАЬCanтАЩt I persuade you to use your influence with the Wellands, Mrs. Mingott? I wasnтАЩt made for long engagements.тАЭ</p>
<p>Old Catherine beamed on him approvingly. тАЬNo; I can see that. YouтАЩve got a quick eye. When you were a little boy IтАЩve no doubt you liked to be helped first.тАЭ She threw back her head with a laugh that made her chins ripple like little waves. тАЬAh, hereтАЩs my Ellen now!тАЭ she exclaimed, as the porti├иres parted behind her.</p>
<p>Madame Olenska came forward with a smile. Her face looked vivid and happy, and she held out her hand gaily to Archer while she stooped to her grandmotherтАЩs kiss.</p>
<p>тАЬI was just saying to him, my dear: тАШNow, why didnтАЩt you marry my little Ellen?тАЩ тАЭ</p>
<p>Madame Olenska looked at Archer, still smiling. тАЬAnd what did he answer?тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬOh, my darling, I leave you to find that out! HeтАЩs been down to Florida to see his sweetheart.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬYes, I know.тАЭ She still looked at him. тАЬI went to see your mother, to ask where youтАЩd gone. I sent a note that you never answered, and I was afraid you were ill.тАЭ</p>
<p>He muttered something about leaving unexpectedly, in a great hurry, and having intended to write to her from St. Augustine.</p>
<p>тАЬAnd of course once you were there you never thought of me again!тАЭ She continued to beam on him with a gaiety that might have been a studied assumption of indifference.</p>
<p>тАЬIf she still needs me, sheтАЩs determined not to let me see it,тАЭ he thought, stung by her manner. He wanted to thank her for having been to see his mother, but under the ancestressтАЩs malicious eye he felt himself tongue-tied and constrained.</p>
<p>тАЬLook at himтБатАФin such hot haste to get married that he took French leave and rushed down to implore the silly girl on his knees! ThatтАЩs something like a loverтБатАФthatтАЩs the way handsome Bob Spicer carried off my poor mother; and then got tired of her before I was weanedтБатАФthough they only had to wait eight months for me! But thereтБатАФyouтАЩre not a Spicer, young man; luckily for you and for May. ItтАЩs only my poor Ellen that has kept any of their wicked blood; the rest of them are all model Mingotts,тАЭ cried the old lady scornfully.</p>
<p>Archer was aware that Madame Olenska, who had seated herself at her grandmotherтАЩs side, was still thoughtfully scrutinising him. The gaiety had faded from her eyes, and she said with great gentleness: тАЬSurely, Granny, we can persuade them between us to do as he wishes.тАЭ</p>
<p>Archer rose to go, and as his hand met Madame OlenskaтАЩs he felt that she was waiting for him to make some allusion to her unanswered letter.</p>
<p>тАЬWhen can I see you?тАЭ he asked, as she walked with him to the door of the room.</p>
<p>тАЬWhenever you like; but it must be soon if you want to see the little house again. I am moving next week.тАЭ</p>
<p>A pang shot through him at the memory of his lamplit hours in the low-studded drawing-room. Few as they had been, they were thick with memories.</p>
<p>тАЬTomorrow evening?тАЭ</p>
<p>She nodded. тАЬTomorrow; yes; but early. IтАЩm going out.тАЭ</p>
<p>The next day was a Sunday, and if she were тАЬgoing outтАЭ on a Sunday evening it could, of course, be only to Mrs. Lemuel StruthersтАЩs. He felt a slight movement of annoyance, not so much at her going there (for he rather liked her going where she pleased in spite of the van der Luydens), but because it was the kind of house at which she was sure to meet Beaufort, where she must have known beforehand that she would meet himтБатАФand where she was probably going for that purpose.</p>
<p>тАЬVery well; tomorrow evening,тАЭ he repeated, inwardly resolved that he would not go early, and that by reaching her door late he would either prevent her from going to Mrs. StruthersтАЩs, or else arrive after she had startedтБатАФwhich, all things considered, would no doubt be the simplest solution.</p>
<hr/>
<p>It was only half-past eight, after all, when he rang the bell under the wisteria; not as late as he had intended by half an hourтБатАФbut a singular restlessness had driven him to her door. He reflected, however, that Mrs. StruthersтАЩs Sunday evenings were not like a ball, and that her guests, as if to minimise their delinquency, usually went early.</p>
<p>The one thing he had not counted on, in entering Madame OlenskaтАЩs hall, was to find hats and overcoats there. Why had she bidden him to come early if she was having people to dine? On a closer inspection of the garments besides which Nastasia was laying his own, his resentment gave way to curiosity. The overcoats were in fact the very strangest he had ever seen under a polite roof; and it took but a glance to assure himself that neither of them belonged to Julius Beaufort. One was a shaggy yellow ulster of тАЬreach-me-downтАЭ cut, the other a very old and rusty cloak with a capeтБатАФsomething like what the French called a тАЬMacfarlane.тАЭ This garment, which appeared to be made for a person of prodigious size, had evidently seen long and hard wear, and its greenish-black folds gave out a moist sawdusty smell suggestive of prolonged sessions against barroom walls. On it lay a ragged grey scarf and an odd felt hat of semiclerical shape.</p>
<p>Archer raised his eyebrows enquiringly at Nastasia, who raised hers in return with a fatalistic тАЬ<i>Gi├б!</i>тАЭ as she threw open the drawing-room door.</p>
<p>The young man saw at once that his hostess was not in the room; then, with surprise, he discovered another lady standing by the fire. This lady, who was long, lean and loosely put together, was clad in raiment intricately looped and fringed, with plaids and stripes and bands of plain colour disposed in a design to which the clue seemed missing. Her hair, which had tried to turn white and only succeeded in fading, was surmounted by a Spanish comb and black lace scarf, and silk mittens, visibly darned, covered her rheumatic hands.</p>
<p>Beside her, in a cloud of cigar-smoke, stood the owners of the two overcoats, both in morning clothes that they had evidently not taken off since morning. In one of the two, Archer, to his surprise, recognised Ned Winsett; the other and older, who was unknown to him, and whose gigantic frame declared him to be the wearer of the тАЬMacfarlane,тАЭ had a feebly leonine head with crumpled grey hair, and moved his arms with large pawing gestures, as though he were distributing lay blessings to a kneeling multitude.</p>
<p>These three persons stood together on the hearthrug, their eyes fixed on an extraordinarily large bouquet of crimson roses, with a knot of purple pansies at their base, that lay on the sofa where Madame Olenska usually sat.</p>
<p>тАЬWhat they must have cost at this seasonтБатАФthough of course itтАЩs the sentiment one cares about!тАЭ the lady was saying in a sighing staccato as Archer came in.</p>
<p>The three turned with surprise at his appearance, and the lady, advancing, held out her hand.</p>
<p>тАЬDear Mr. ArcherтБатАФalmost my cousin Newland!тАЭ she said. тАЬI am the Marchioness Manson.тАЭ</p>
<p>Archer bowed, and she continued: тАЬMy Ellen has taken me in for a few days. I came from Cuba, where I have been spending the winter with Spanish friendsтБатАФsuch delightful distinguished people: the highest nobility of old CastileтБатАФhow I wish you could know them! But I was called away by our dear great friend here, Dr. Carver. You donтАЩt know Dr. Agathon Carver, founder of the Valley of Love Community?тАЭ</p>
<p>Dr. Carver inclined his leonine head, and the Marchioness continued: тАЬAh, New YorkтБатАФNew YorkтБатАФhow little the life of the spirit has reached it! But I see you do know Mr. Winsett.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬOh, yesтБатАФ<em>I</em> reached him some time ago; but not by that route,тАЭ Winsett said with his dry smile.</p>
<p>The Marchioness shook her head reprovingly. тАЬHow do you know, Mr. Winsett? The spirit bloweth where it listeth.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬListтБатАФoh, list!тАЭ interjected Dr. Carver in a stentorian murmur.</p>
<p>тАЬBut do sit down, Mr. Archer. We four have been having a delightful little dinner together, and my child has gone up to dress. She expects you; she will be down in a moment. We were just admiring these marvellous flowers, which will surprise her when she reappears.тАЭ</p>
<p>Winsett remained on his feet. тАЬIтАЩm afraid I must be off. Please tell Madame Olenska that we shall all feel lost when she abandons our street. This house has been an oasis.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬAh, but she wonтАЩt abandon <em>you</em>. Poetry and art are the breath of life to her. It <em>is</em> poetry you write, Mr. Winsett?тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬWell, no; but I sometimes read it,тАЭ said Winsett, including the group in a general nod and slipping out of the room.</p>
<p>тАЬA caustic spiritтБатАФ<i>un peu sauvage</i>. But so witty; Dr. Carver, you <em>do</em> think him witty?тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬI never think of wit,тАЭ said Dr. Carver severely.</p>
<p>тАЬAhтБатАФahтБатАФyou never think of wit! How merciless he is to us weak mortals, Mr. Archer! But he lives only in the life of the spirit; and tonight he is mentally preparing the lecture he is to deliver presently at Mrs. BlenkerтАЩs. Dr. Carver, would there be time, before you start for the BlenkersтАЩ to explain to Mr. Archer your illuminating discovery of the Direct Contact? But no; I see it is nearly nine oтАЩclock, and we have no right to detain you while so many are waiting for your message.тАЭ</p>
<p>Dr. Carver looked slightly disappointed at this conclusion, but, having compared his ponderous gold timepiece with Madame OlenskaтАЩs little travelling-clock, he reluctantly gathered up his mighty limbs for departure.</p>
<p>тАЬI shall see you later, dear friend?тАЭ he suggested to the Marchioness, who replied with a smile: тАЬAs soon as EllenтАЩs carriage comes I will join you; I do hope the lecture wonтАЩt have begun.тАЭ</p>
<p>Dr. Carver looked thoughtfully at Archer. тАЬPerhaps, if this young gentleman is interested in my experiences, Mrs. Blenker might allow you to bring him with you?тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬOh, dear friend, if it were possibleтБатАФI am sure she would be too happy. But I fear my Ellen counts on Mr. Archer herself.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬThat,тАЭ said Dr. Carver, тАЬis unfortunateтБатАФbut here is my card.тАЭ He handed it to Archer, who read on it, in Gothic characters:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Agathon Carver<br/>The Valley of Love<br/>Kittasquattamy, N. Y.</p></blockquote>
<p>Dr. Carver bowed himself out, and Mrs. Manson, with a sigh that might have been either of regret or relief, again waved Archer to a seat.</p>
<p>тАЬEllen will be down in a moment; and before she comes, I am so glad of this quiet moment with you.тАЭ</p>
<p>Archer murmured his pleasure at their meeting, and the Marchioness continued, in her low sighing accents: тАЬI know everything, dear Mr. ArcherтБатАФmy child has told me all you have done for her. Your wise advice: your courageous firmnessтБатАФthank heaven it was not too late!тАЭ</p>
<p>The young man listened with considerable embarrassment. Was there anyone, he wondered, to whom Madame Olenska had not proclaimed his intervention in her private affairs?</p>
<p>тАЬMadame Olenska exaggerates; I simply gave her a legal opinion, as she asked me to.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬAh, but in doing itтБатАФin doing it you were the unconscious instrument ofтБатАФofтБатАФwhat word have we moderns for Providence, Mr. Archer?тАЭ cried the lady, tilting her head on one side and drooping her lids mysteriously. тАЬLittle did you know that at that very moment I was being appealed to: being approached, in factтБатАФfrom the other side of the Atlantic!тАЭ</p>
<p>She glanced over her shoulder, as though fearful of being overheard, and then, drawing her chair nearer, and raising a tiny ivory fan to her lips, breathed behind it: тАЬBy the Count himselfтБатАФmy poor, mad, foolish Olenski; who asks only to take her back on her own terms.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬGood God!тАЭ Archer exclaimed, springing up.</p>
<p>тАЬYou are horrified? Yes, of course; I understand. I donтАЩt defend poor Stanislas, though he has always called me his best friend. He does not defend himselfтБатАФhe casts himself at her feet: in my person.тАЭ She tapped her emaciated bosom. тАЬI have his letter here.тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬA letter?тБатАФHas Madame Olenska seen it?тАЭ Archer stammered, his brain whirling with the shock of the announcement.</p>
<p>The Marchioness Manson shook her head softly. тАЬTimeтБатАФtime; I must have time. I know my EllenтБатАФhaughty, intractable; shall I say, just a shade unforgiving?тАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬBut, good heavens, to forgive is one thing; to go back into that hellтБатАФтАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬAh, yes,тАЭ the Marchioness acquiesced. тАЬSo she describes itтБатАФmy sensitive child! But on the material side, Mr. Archer, if one may stoop to consider such things; do you know what she is giving up? Those roses there on the sofaтБатАФacres like them, under glass and in the open, in his matchless terraced gardens at Nice! JewelsтБатАФhistoric pearls: the Sobieski emeraldsтБатАФsablesтБатАФbut she cares nothing for all these! Art and beauty, those she does care for, she lives for, as I always have; and those also surrounded her. Pictures, priceless furniture, music, brilliant conversationтБатАФah, that, my dear young man, if youтАЩll excuse me, is what youтАЩve no conception of here! And she had it all; and the homage of the greatest. She tells me she is not thought handsome in New YorkтБатАФgood heavens! Her portrait has been painted nine times; the greatest artists in Europe have begged for the privilege. Are these things nothing? And the remorse of an adoring husband?тАЭ</p>
<p>As the Marchioness Manson rose to her climax her face assumed an expression of ecstatic retrospection which would have moved ArcherтАЩs mirth had he not been numb with amazement.</p>
<p>He would have laughed if anyone had foretold to him that his first sight of poor Medora Manson would have been in the guise of a messenger of Satan; but he was in no mood for laughing now, and she seemed to him to come straight out of the hell from which Ellen Olenska had just escaped.</p>
<p>тАЬShe knows nothing yetтБатАФof all this?тАЭ he asked abruptly.</p>
<p>Mrs. Manson laid a purple finger on her lips. тАЬNothing directlyтБатАФbut does she suspect? Who can tell? The truth is, Mr. Archer, I have been waiting to see you. From the moment I heard of the firm stand you had taken, and of your influence over her, I hoped it might be possible to count on your supportтБатАФto convince youтБа тБатАжтАЭ</p>
<p>тАЬThat she ought to go back? I would rather see her dead!тАЭ cried the young man violently.</p>
<p>тАЬAh,тАЭ the Marchioness murmured, without visible resentment. For a while she sat in her armchair, opening and shutting the absurd ivory fan between her mittened fingers; but suddenly she lifted her head and listened.</p>
<p>тАЬHere she comes,тАЭ she said in a rapid whisper; and then, pointing to the bouquet on the sofa: тАЬAm I to understand that you prefer <em>that</em>, Mr. Archer? After all, marriage is marriageтБа тБатАж and my niece is still a wifeтБа тБатАжтАЭ</p>
</chapter>
</document>