<document uuid="CD42vpYD26bn7Dnd6LOEF">
<meta>
<copyright>CC0/PD. No rights reserved</copyright>
<source url="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/o-henry/short-fiction">Standard Ebooks</source>
<title>He Also Serves</title>
</meta>
<chapter>
<p>If I could have a thousand years‚ÅÝ‚Äîjust one little thousand years‚ÅÝ‚Äîmore of life, I might, in that time, draw near enough to true Romance to touch the hem of her robe.</p>
<p>Up from ships men come, and from waste places and forest and road and garret and cellar to maunder to me in strangely distributed words of the things they have seen and considered. The recording of their tales is no more than a matter of ears and fingers. There are only two fates I dread‚ÅÝ‚Äîdeafness and writer‚Äôs cramp. The hand is yet steady; let the ear bear the blame if these printed words be not in the order they were delivered to me by Hunky Magee, true camp-follower of fortune.</p>
<p>Biography shall claim you but an instant‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI first knew Hunky when he was headwaiter at Chubb‚Äôs little beefsteak restaurant and caf√© on Third Avenue. There was only one waiter besides.</p>
<p>Then, successively, I caromed against him in the little streets of the Big City after his trip to Alaska, his voyage as cook with a treasure-seeking expedition to the Caribbean, and his failure as a pearl-fisher in the Arkansas River. Between these dashes into the land of adventure he usually came back to Chubb‚Äôs for a while. Chubb‚Äôs was a port for him when gales blew too high; but when you dined there and Hunky went for your steak you never knew whether he would come to anchor in the kitchen or in the Malayan Archipelago. You wouldn‚Äôt care for his description‚ÅÝ‚Äîhe was soft of voice and hard of face, and rarely had to use more than one eye to quell any approach to a disturbance among Chubb‚Äôs customers.</p>
<p>One night I found Hunky standing at a corner of Twenty-third Street and Third Avenue after an absence of several months. In ten minutes we had a little round table between us in a quiet corner, and my ears began to get busy. I leave out my sly ruses and feints to draw Hunky‚Äôs word-of-mouth blows‚ÅÝ‚Äîit all came to something like this:</p>
<p>‚ÄúSpeaking of the next election,‚Äù said Hunky, ‚Äúdid you ever know much about Indians? No? I don‚Äôt mean the Cooper, Beadle, cigar-store, or Laughing Water kind‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI mean the modern Indian‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe kind that takes Greek prizes in colleges and scalps the halfback on the other side in football games. The kind that eats macaroons and tea in the afternoons with the daughter of the professor of biology, and fills up on grasshoppers and fried rattlesnake when they get back to the ancestral wickiup.</p>
<p>‚ÄúWell, they ain‚Äôt so bad. I like ‚Äôem better than most foreigners that have come over in the last few hundred years. One thing about the Indian is this: when he mixes with the white race he swaps all his own vices for them of the palefaces‚ÅÝ‚Äîand he retains all his own virtues. Well, his virtues are enough to call out the reserves whenever he lets ‚Äôem loose. But the imported foreigners adopt our virtues and keep their own vices‚ÅÝ‚Äîand it‚Äôs going to take our whole standing army some day to police that gang.</p>
<p>‚ÄúBut let me tell you about the trip I took to Mexico with High Jack Snakefeeder, a Cherokee twice removed, a graduate of a Pennsylvania college and the latest thing in pointed-toed, rubber-heeled, patent kid moccasins and Madras hunting-shirt with turned-back cuffs. He was a friend of mine. I met him in Tahlequah when I was out there during the land boom, and we got thick. He had got all there was out of colleges and had come back to lead his people out of Egypt. He was a man of first-class style and wrote essays, and had been invited to visit rich guys‚Äô houses in Boston and such places.</p>
<p>‚ÄúThere was a Cherokee girl in Muscogee that High Jack was foolish about. He took me to see her a few times. Her name was Florence Blue Feather‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut you want to clear your mind of all ideas of squaws with nose-rings and army blankets. This young lady was whiter than you are, and better educated than I ever was. You couldn‚Äôt have told her from any of the girls shopping in the swell Third Avenue stores. I liked her so well that I got to calling on her now and then when High Jack wasn‚Äôt along, which is the way of friends in such matters. She was educated at the Muscogee College, and was making a specialty of‚ÅÝ‚Äîlet‚Äôs see‚ÅÝ‚Äîeth‚ÅÝ‚Äîyes, ethnology. That‚Äôs the art that goes back and traces the descent of different races of people, leading up from jellyfish through monkeys and to the O‚ÄôBriens. High Jack had took up that line too, and had read papers about it before all kinds of riotous assemblies‚ÅÝ‚ÄîChautauquas and Choctaws and chowder-parties, and such. Having a mutual taste for musty information like that was what made ‚Äôem like each other, I suppose. But I don‚Äôt know! What they call congeniality of tastes ain‚Äôt always it. Now, when Miss Blue Feather and me was talking together, I listened to her affidavits about the first families of the Land of Nod being cousins german (well, if the Germans don‚Äôt nod, who does?) to the mound-builders of Ohio with incomprehension and respect. And when I‚Äôd tell her about the Bowery and Coney Island, and sing her a few songs that I‚Äôd heard the Jamaica niggers sing at their church lawn-parties, she didn‚Äôt look much less interested than she did when High Jack would tell her that he had a pipe that the first inhabitants of America originally arrived here on stilts after a freshet at Tenafly, New Jersey.</p>
<p>‚ÄúBut I was going to tell you more about High Jack.</p>
<p>‚ÄúAbout six months ago I get a letter from him, saying he‚Äôd been commissioned by the Minority Report Bureau of Ethnology at Washington to go down to Mexico and translate some excavations or dig up the meaning of some shorthand notes on some ruins‚ÅÝ‚Äîor something of that sort. And if I‚Äôd go along he could squeeze the price into the expense account.</p>
<p>‚ÄúWell, I‚Äôd been holding a napkin over my arm at Chubb‚Äôs about long enough then, so I wired High Jack ‚ÄòYes‚Äô; and he sent me a ticket, and I met him in Washington, and he had a lot of news to tell me. First of all, was that Florence Blue Feather had suddenly disappeared from her home and environments.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòRun away?‚Äô I asked.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòVanished,‚Äô says High Jack. ‚ÄòDisappeared like your shadow when the sun goes under a cloud. She was seen on the street, and then she turned a corner and nobody ever seen her afterward. The whole community turned out to look for her, but we never found a clue.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòThat‚Äôs bad‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat‚Äôs bad,‚Äô says I. ‚ÄòShe was a mighty nice girl, and as smart as you find em.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúHigh Jack seemed to take it hard. I guess he must have esteemed Miss Blue Feather quite highly. I could see that he‚Äôd referred the matter to the whiskey-jug. That was his weak point‚ÅÝ‚Äîand many another man‚Äôs. I‚Äôve noticed that when a man loses a girl he generally takes to drink either just before or just after it happens.</p>
<p>‚ÄúFrom Washington we railroaded it to New Orleans, and there took a tramp steamer bound for Belize. And a gale pounded us all down the Caribbean, and nearly wrecked us on the Yucatan coast opposite a little town without a harbor called Boca de Coacoyula. Suppose the ship had run against that name in the dark!</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòBetter fifty years of Europe than a cyclone in the bay,‚Äô says High Jack Snakefeeder. So we get the captain to send us ashore in a dory when the squall seemed to cease from squalling.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòWe will find ruins here or make ‚Äôem,‚Äô says High. ‚ÄòThe Government doesn‚Äôt care which we do. An appropriation is an appropriation.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúBoca de Coacoyula was a dead town. Them biblical towns we read about‚ÅÝ‚ÄîTired and Siphon‚ÅÝ‚Äîafter they was destroyed, they must have looked like Forty-second Street and Broadway compared to this Boca place. It still claimed 1300 inhabitants as estimated and engraved on the stone courthouse by the census-taker in 1597. The citizens were a mixture of Indians and other Indians; but some of ‚Äôem was light-colored, which I was surprised to see. The town was huddled up on the shore, with woods so thick around it that a subpoena-server couldn‚Äôt have reached a monkey ten yards away with the papers. We wondered what kept it from being annexed to Kansas; but we soon found out that it was Major Bing.</p>
<p>‚ÄúMajor Bing was the ointment around the fly. He had the cochineal, sarsaparilla, logwood, annatto, hemp, and all other dyewoods and pure food adulteration concessions cornered. He had five-sixths of the Boca de Thingama-jiggers working for him on shares. It was a beautiful graft. We used to brag about Morgan and E. H. and others of our wisest when I was in the provinces‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut now no more. That peninsula has got our little country turned into a submarine without even the observation tower showing.</p>
<p>‚ÄúMajor Bing‚Äôs idea was this. He had the population go forth into the forest and gather these products. When they brought ‚Äôem in he gave ‚Äôem one-fifth for their trouble. Sometimes they‚Äôd strike and demand a sixth. The Major always gave in to ‚Äôem.</p>
<p>‚ÄúThe Major had a bungalow so close on the sea that the nine-inch tide seeped through the cracks in the kitchen floor. Me and him and High Jack Snakefeeder sat on the porch and drank rum from noon till midnight. He said he had piled up $300,000 in New Orleans banks, and High and me could stay with him forever if we would. But High Jack happened to think of the United States, and began to talk ethnology.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòRuins!‚Äô says Major Bing. ‚ÄòThe woods are full of ‚Äôem. I don‚Äôt know how far they date back, but they was here before I came.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúHigh Jack asks what form of worship the citizens of that locality are addicted to.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòWhy,‚Äô says the Major, rubbing his nose, ‚ÄòI can‚Äôt hardly say. I imagine it‚Äôs infidel or Aztec or Nonconformist or something like that. There‚Äôs a church here‚ÅÝ‚Äîa Methodist or some other kind‚ÅÝ‚Äîwith a parson named Skidder. He claims to have converted the people to Christianity. He and me don‚Äôt assimilate except on state occasions. I imagine they worship some kind of gods or idols yet. But Skidder says he has ‚Äôem in the fold.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúA few days later High Jack and me, prowling around, strikes a plain path into the forest, and follows it a good four miles. Then a branch turns to the left. We go a mile, maybe, down that, and run up against the finest ruin you ever saw‚ÅÝ‚Äîsolid stone with trees and vines and underbrush all growing up against it and in it and through it. All over it was chiselled carvings of funny beasts and people that would have been arrested if they‚Äôd ever come out in vaudeville that way. We approached it from the rear.</p>
<p>‚ÄúHigh Jack had been drinking too much rum ever since we landed in Boca. You know how an Indian is‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe palefaces fixed his clock when they introduced him to firewater. He‚Äôd brought a quart along with him.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòHunky,‚Äô says he, ‚Äòwe‚Äôll explore the ancient temple. It may be that the storm that landed us here was propitious. The Minority Report Bureau of Ethnology,‚Äô says he, ‚Äòmay yet profit by the vagaries of wind and tide.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúWe went in the rear door of the bum edifice. We struck a kind of alcove without bath. There was a granite davenport, and a stone washstand without any soap or exit for the water, and some hardwood pegs drove into holes in the wall, and that was all. To go out of that furnished apartment into a Harlem hall bedroom would make you feel like getting back home from an amateur violoncello solo at an East Side Settlement house.</p>
<p>‚ÄúWhile High was examining some hieroglyphics on the wall that the stonemasons must have made when their tools slipped, I stepped into the front room. That was at least thirty by fifty feet, stone floor, six little windows like square portholes that didn‚Äôt let much light in.</p>
<p>‚ÄúI looked back over my shoulder, and sees High Jack‚Äôs face three feet away.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòHigh,‚Äô says I, ‚Äòof all the‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúAnd then I noticed he looked funny, and I turned around.</p>
<p>‚ÄúHe‚Äôd taken off his clothes to the waist, and he didn‚Äôt seem to hear me. I touched him, and came near beating it. High Jack had turned to stone. I had been drinking some rum myself.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòOssified!‚Äô I says to him, loudly. ‚ÄòI knew what would happen if you kept it up.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúAnd then High Jack comes in from the alcove when he hears me conversing with nobody, and we have a look at Mr. Snakefeeder No. 2. It‚Äôs a stone idol, or god, or revised statute or something, and it looks as much like High Jack as one green pea looks like itself. It‚Äôs got exactly his face and size and color, but it‚Äôs steadier on its pins. It stands on a kind of rostrum or pedestal, and you can see it‚Äôs been there ten million years.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòHe‚Äôs a cousin of mine,‚Äô sings High, and then he turns solemn.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòHunky,‚Äô he says, putting one hand on my shoulder and one on the statue‚Äôs, ‚ÄòI‚Äôm in the holy temple of my ancestors.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòWell, if looks goes for anything,‚Äô says I, ‚Äòyou‚Äôve struck a twin. Stand side by side with buddy, and let‚Äôs see if there‚Äôs any difference.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúThere wasn‚Äôt. You know an Indian can keep his face as still as an iron dog‚Äôs when he wants to, so when High Jack froze his features you couldn‚Äôt have told him from the other one.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòThere‚Äôs some letters,‚Äô says I, ‚Äòon his nob‚Äôs pedestal, but I can‚Äôt make ‚Äôem out. The alphabet of this country seems to be composed of sometimes <i>a</i>, <i>e</i>, <i>i</i>, <i>o</i>, and <i>u</i>, but generally <i>z</i>‚Äôs, <i>l</i>‚Äôs, and <i>t</i>‚Äôs.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúHigh Jack‚Äôs ethnology gets the upper hand of his rum for a minute, and he investigates the inscription.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòHunky,‚Äô says he, ‚Äòthis is a statue of Tlotopaxl, one of the most powerful gods of the ancient Aztecs.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòGlad to know him,‚Äô says I, ‚Äòbut in his present condition he reminds me of the joke Shakespeare got off on Julius Caesar. We might say about your friend:</p>
<poem>
<p><span>‚Äú ‚ÄòImperious what‚Äôs-his-name, dead and turned to stone‚ÅÝ‚Äî</span><br/><span>No use to write or call him on the phone.‚Äô</span></p></poem>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòHunky,‚Äô says High Jack Snakefeeder, looking at me funny, ‚Äòdo you believe in reincarnation?‚Äô</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòIt sounds to me,‚Äô says I, ‚Äòlike either a cleanup of the slaughterhouses or a new kind of Boston pink. I don‚Äôt know.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòI believe,‚Äô says he, ‚Äòthat I am the reincarnation of Tlotopaxl. My researches have convinced me that the Cherokees, of all the North American tribes, can boast of the straightest descent from the proud Aztec race. That,‚Äô says he, ‚Äòwas a favorite theory of mine and Florence Blue Feather‚Äôs. And she‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhat if she‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúHigh Jack grabs my arm and walls his eyes at me. Just then he looked more like his eminent co-Indian murderer, Crazy Horse.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòWell,‚Äô says I, ‚Äòwhat if she, what if she, what if she? You‚Äôre drunk,‚Äô says I. ‚ÄòImpersonating idols and believing in‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhat was it?‚ÅÝ‚Äîrecarnalization? Let‚Äôs have a drink,‚Äô says I. ‚ÄòIt‚Äôs as spooky here as a Brooklyn artificial-limb factory at midnight with the gas turned down.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúJust then I heard somebody coming, and I dragged High Jack into the bedless bedchamber. There was peepholes bored through the wall, so we could see the whole front part of the temple. Major Bing told me afterward that the ancient priests in charge used to rubber through them at the congregation.</p>
<p>‚ÄúIn a few minutes an old Indian woman came in with a big oval earthen dish full of grub. She set it on a square block of stone in front of the graven image, and laid down and walloped her face on the floor a few times, and then took a walk for herself.</p>
<p>‚ÄúHigh Jack and me was hungry, so we came out and looked it over. There was goat steaks and fried rice-cakes, and plantains and cassava, and broiled land-crabs and mangoes‚ÅÝ‚Äînothing like what you get at Chubb‚Äôs.</p>
<p>‚ÄúWe ate hearty‚ÅÝ‚Äîand had another round of rum.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòIt must be old Tecumseh‚Äôs‚ÅÝ‚Äîor whatever you call him‚ÅÝ‚Äîbirthday,‚Äô says I. ‚ÄòOr do they feed him every day? I thought gods only drank vanilla on Mount Catawampus.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúThen some more native parties in short kimonos that showed their aboriginees punctured the near-horizon, and me and High had to skip back into Father Axletree‚Äôs private boudoir. They came by ones, twos, and threes, and left all sorts of offerings‚ÅÝ‚Äîthere was enough grub for Bingham‚Äôs nine gods of war, with plenty left over for the Peace Conference at The Hague. They brought jars of honey, and bunches of bananas, and bottles of wine, and stacks of tortillas, and beautiful shawls worth one hundred dollars apiece that the Indian women weave of a kind of vegetable fibre like silk. All of ‚Äôem got down and wriggled on the floor in front of that hard-finish god, and then sneaked off through the woods again.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòI wonder who gets this rake-off?‚Äô remarks High Jack.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòOh,‚Äô says I, ‚Äòthere‚Äôs priests or deputy idols or a committee of disarrangements somewhere in the woods on the job. Wherever you find a god you‚Äôll find somebody waiting to take charge of the burnt offerings.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúAnd then we took another swig of rum and walked out to the parlor front door to cool off, for it was as hot inside as a summer camp on the Palisades.</p>
<p>‚ÄúAnd while we stood there in the breeze we looks down the path and sees a young lady approaching the blasted ruin. She was barefooted and had on a white robe, and carried a wreath of white flowers in her hand. When she got nearer we saw she had a long blue feather stuck through her black hair. And when she got nearer still me and High Jack Snakefeeder grabbed each other to keep from tumbling down on the floor; for the girl‚Äôs face was as much like Florence Blue Feather‚Äôs as his was like old King Toxicology‚Äôs.</p>
<p>‚ÄúAnd then was when High Jack‚Äôs booze drowned his system of ethnology. He dragged me inside back of the statue, and says:</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòLay hold of it, Hunky. We‚Äôll pack it into the other room. I felt it all the time,‚Äô says he. ‚ÄòI‚Äôm the reconsideration of the god Locomotorataxia, and Florence Blue Feather was my bride a thousand years ago. She has come to seek me in the temple where I used to reign.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòAll right,‚Äô says I. ‚ÄòThere‚Äôs no use arguing against the rum question. You take his feet.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúWe lifted the three-hundred-pound stone god, and carried him into the back room of the caf√©‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe temple, I mean‚ÅÝ‚Äîand leaned him against the wall. It was more work than bouncing three live ones from an all-night Broadway joint on New-Year‚Äôs Eve.</p>
<p>‚ÄúThen High Jack ran out and brought in a couple of them Indian silk shawls and began to undress himself.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòOh, figs!‚Äô says I. ‚ÄòIs it thus? Strong drink is an adder and subtractor, too. Is it the heat or the call of the wild that‚Äôs got you?‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúBut High Jack is too full of exaltation and cane-juice to reply. He stops the disrobing business just short of the Manhattan Beach rules, and then winds them red-and-white shawls around him, and goes out and stands on the pedestal as steady as any platinum deity you ever saw. And I looks through a peek-hole to see what he is up to.</p>
<p>‚ÄúIn a few minutes in comes the girl with the flower wreath. Danged if I wasn‚Äôt knocked a little silly when she got close, she looked so exactly much like Florence Blue Feather. ‚ÄòI wonder,‚Äô says I to myself, ‚Äòif she has been reincarcerated, too? If I could see,‚Äô says I to myself, ‚Äòwhether she has a mole on her left‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äô But the next minute I thought she looked one-eighth of a shade darker than Florence; but she looked good at that. And High Jack hadn‚Äôt drunk all the rum that had been drank.</p>
<p>‚ÄúThe girl went up within ten feet of the bum idol, and got down and massaged her nose with the floor, like the rest did. Then she went nearer and laid the flower wreath on the block of stone at High Jack‚Äôs feet. Rummy as I was, I thought it was kind of nice of her to think of offering flowers instead of household and kitchen provisions. Even a stone god ought to appreciate a little sentiment like that on top of the fancy groceries they had piled up in front of him.</p>
<p>‚ÄúAnd then High Jack steps down from his pedestal, quiet, and mentions a few words that sounded just like the hieroglyphics carved on the walls of the ruin. The girl gives a little jump backward, and her eyes fly open as big as doughnuts; but she don‚Äôt beat it.</p>
<p>‚ÄúWhy didn‚Äôt she? I‚Äôll tell you why I think why. It don‚Äôt seem to a girl so supernatural, unlikely, strange, and startling that a stone god should come to life for <em>her</em>. If he was to do it for one of them snub-nosed brown girls on the other side of the woods, now, it would be different‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut <em>her</em>! I‚Äôll bet she said to herself: ‚ÄòWell, goodness me! you‚Äôve been a long time getting on your job. I‚Äôve half a mind not to speak to you.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúBut she and High Jack holds hands and walks away out of the temple together. By the time I‚Äôd had time to take another drink and enter upon the scene they was twenty yards away, going up the path in the woods that the girl had come down. With the natural scenery already in place, it was just like a play to watch ‚Äôem‚ÅÝ‚Äîshe looking up at him, and him giving her back the best that an Indian can hand, out in the way of a goo-goo eye. But there wasn‚Äôt anything in that recarnification and revulsion to tintype for me.</p>
<p>‚Äú ‚ÄòHey! Injun!‚Äô I yells out to High Jack. ‚ÄòWe‚Äôve got a board-bill due in town, and you‚Äôre leaving me without a cent. Brace up and cut out the Neapolitan fisher-maiden, and let‚Äôs go back home.‚Äô</p>
<p>‚ÄúBut on the two goes; without looking once back until, as you might say, the forest swallowed ‚Äôem up. And I never saw or heard of High Jack Snakefeeder from that day to this. I don‚Äôt know if the Cherokees came from the Aspics; but if they did, one of ‚Äôem went back.</p>
<p>‚ÄúAll I could do was to hustle back to that Boca place and panhandle Major Bing. He detached himself from enough of his winnings to buy me a ticket home. And I‚Äôm back again on the job at Chubb‚Äôs, sir, and I‚Äôm going to hold it steady. Come round, and you‚Äôll find the steaks as good as ever.‚Äù</p>
<p>I wondered what Hunky Magee thought about his own story; so I asked him if he had any theories about reincarnation and transmogrification and such mysteries as he had touched upon.</p>
<p>‚ÄúNothing like that,‚Äù said Hunky, positively. ‚ÄúWhat ailed High Jack was too much booze and education. They‚Äôll do an Indian up every time.‚Äù</p>
<p>‚ÄúBut what about Miss Blue Feather?‚Äù I persisted.</p>
<p>‚ÄúSay,‚Äù said Hunky, with a grin, ‚Äúthat little lady that stole High Jack certainly did give me a jar when I first took a look at her, but it was only for a minute. You remember I told you High Jack said that Miss Florence Blue Feather disappeared from home about a year ago? Well, where she landed four days later was in as neat a five-room flat on East Twenty-third Street as you ever walked sideways through‚ÅÝ‚Äîand she‚Äôs been Mrs. Magee ever since.‚Äù</p>
</chapter>
</document>