<document uuid="CD42vgUWs3shCs8BW1yZa">
<meta>
<copyright>CC0/PD. No rights reserved</copyright>
<source url="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/o-henry/short-fiction">Standard Ebooks</source>
<title>The Telegram</title>
</meta>
<chapter>
<p>Scene: Telegraph office in Houston.</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr><td/><td><stage-direction>Enter handsome black velour cape, trimmed with jet and braid, with Tibetan fur collar, all enclosing lovely young lady.</stage-direction></td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Oh, I want to send a telegram at once, if you please. Give me about six blanks, please. <stage-direction>Writes about ten minutes.</stage-direction> How much will this amount to, please?</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Clerk</persona><td><stage-direction>Counting words.</stage-direction> Sixteen dollars and ninety-five cents, ma’am.</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Goodness gracious! I’ve only thirty cents with me. <stage-direction>Suspiciously.</stage-direction> How is it you charge so much, when the post-office only requires two cents?</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Clerk</persona><td>We claim to deliver messages quicker than the post-office, ma’am. You can send ten words to Waco for twenty-five cents.</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Give me another blank, please: I guess that will be enough. <stage-direction>After five minutes’ hard work she produces the following: “Ring was awfully lovely. Come down as soon as you can. Mamie.”</stage-direction></td></tr>
<tr><persona>Clerk</persona><td>This contains eleven words. That will be thirty cents.</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Oh, gracious! I wanted that nickel to buy gum with.</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Clerk</persona><td>Let’s see. You might strike out, “awfully,” and that will make it all right.</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Indeed I shan’t. You ought to see that ring. I’ll give you the thirty cents.</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Clerk</persona><td>To whom is this to be sent?</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>It seems to me you are rather inquisitive, sir.</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Clerk</persona><td><stage-direction>Wearily.</stage-direction> I assure you there is no personal interest expressed in the question. We have to know the name and address in order to send the message.</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Oh, yes. I didn’t think of that. <stage-direction>She writes the name and address, pays the thirty cents and departs. Twenty minutes later she returns, out of breath.</stage-direction></td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Oh, I forgot something. Have you sent it off yet?</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Clerk</persona><td>Yes, ten minutes ago.</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Oh, I’m so sorry. It isn’t the way I wanted it at all. Can’t you telegraph and have it changed for me?</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Clerk</persona><td>Is it anything important?</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Yes: I wanted to underscore the words “awfully lovely.” Will you have that attended to at once?</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Clerk</persona><td>Certainly, and we have some real nice violet extract; would you like a few drops on your telegram?</td></tr>
<tr><persona>Young lady</persona><td>Oh, yes: so kind of you. I expect to send all my telegrams through your office, you have been so accommodating. Good morning.</td></tr></tbody>
</table>
</chapter>
</document>